Thank you.
Thank you.
In the Sensai Academia Sinica, the knowledge-response lecture in May begins.
In the森塞中央研究院5月份知识响验演讲会开始.
Please start.
Please start.
Thank you.
Thank you.
Let's welcome 또An Jun's knowledge experience this month to all of you.
Let's welcome 또安军此月的知识响验 to all of you.
The jury personally from the graduate uzutian
The jury personally from the graduate uzutian
of Sheg suggestion Department of Roblox goodbye
of Sheg suggestion Department of Roblox goodbye不得了
Dr. Wu Zhixiong graduated from the Department of Practice, National Taiwan University
吳志雄博士是台大實務系畢業的
Afterwards, he obtained a master's degree from the Institute of Biochemistry of National Taiwan University
之後他在台大的生物化學研究所得到碩士學位
National Taiwan University Biochemistry is also co-organized with Academia Sinica
台大生物化學也是跟中研院合辦的
So it is also the Institute of Biochemistry of Academia Sinica
所以也是中研院的生化所
Then joined the team of this biochemical institute to do research
之後又加入了這個生化所的團隊做研究
Later came to the United States to study
後來到了美國留學
Went to Wisconsin Medicine to get a Ph.D. in Medicinal Chemistry
到Wisconsin Medicine得到了博士學位是藥物化學的
He was taught by the very famous Charles C.
他跟著教授是非常有名的Charles C
Then I returned to Taiwan and returned to the Institute of Biochemistry
之後又回到台灣 回到生化所
The Biochemical Institute was established here in 1995
生化所在1995年的時候在這裡成立
The building that can be seen now
現在可以看到的大樓
At that time, Dr. Wu also moved to Academia Sinica
那個時候吳博士也就搬到中研院來
So from the front in
所以從前面在
After master's degree and after working as an assistant
在碩士後來在當助理之後
be a researcher here
在這裡當研究員
43 years in total
整個總共43年
Now a so-called Special Review Researcher
現在是所謂的特評研究員
Research work without Boss
無波士的研究工作
Mainly the relationship between the structure and function of biochemical molecules
主要是生化分子的結構跟功能的關係
Both small and large molecules
包括小分子也包括大分子
e.g. proteoglycans
譬如說是蛋白質多醣體
Thinking of polysaccharides
想到多醣體的話
Boss in fact
事實上無波士
An important field of research is Tang science
一個重要的研究領域就是唐科學
Let me tell you that Tang Science is actually a strong point of traditional Chinese medicine hospital
我講一下唐科學事實上中醫院是一個強項
In fact, it is known in the world that the Chinese Medicine Hospital
事實上在世界上都知道說中醫院
is doing very well in this regard
在這方面是做得非常好
In the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine related to Tang Science
在中醫院裡面跟唐科學有關的
number of researchers
做研究員的數目
should be in the world
應該可以是在世界上
When comparing in different universities
做在不同的大學裡面比較的話
should be
應該是
It belongs to Saul, that is, the number of researchers who do Tang science
是在屬於索爾的,就是做唐科學的研究員的數目
In this case, think about talking about this background
這個的話,想想稍微講一下這個background
In the early days, Academician Chuan Li suggested to promote the scientific research of Tang Dynasty
早期的時候是李院穿院士建議推動這個唐科學的研究
He suggested Dr. Liu Deyong to be the director of the Institute of Biochemistry
他就建議了劉德勇博士來做生化所的所長
Then Director Liu also invited to work with Academician Chuan Li
然後劉所長也邀請到跟李院穿院士一起努力
Japanese professor Jing Miao Enoe came to the Institute of Biochemistry to learn about it
日本的教授警喪Enoe到生化所來認知
This is the beginning of some scientific research by Tang
這就開始展開一些唐科學的研究
At the same time, some researchers
同時也沿來一些研究員
Of course, later, after the head of Weng District Committee returned to Taiwan,
當然到後來,翁區委院長回到台灣之後
It further promoted the research of Tang Science
更推廣了唐科學的研究
It is also difficult for more researchers to invest in this area
也延難到更多人在這方面投入的研究員
If nothing is lost, even in this field
無不失的話就算是在這個領域
Be a Pioneer at Academia Sinica
在中研院是一個先驅者
started doing it very early
很早就開始做了
The other question is that he gave some international organizations
那另外一題就是他對國際上的一些組織
Also active is very involved
也活動是很投入
For example, he often participates in
譬如說是他經常參加
ACGG stands for Asian Community of Glycobiology
ACGG就是Asian Community of Glycobiology
Glycotechnology
Glycotechnology
And Cylo Glycobiology
還有Cylo Glycobiology
Nesalogy is Tropic Acid
Nesalogy是托伊酸
Our two societies are international societies
我們這兩個學會是國際的學會
Also done in Taiwan
也在台灣辦過
Their knowledge should be the conference of the international society
他們的學識是應該是國際上的學會的會議
The other thing to mention is that he is accepting
另外要提的就是說是他在接受了
Professor InternetWay later
InternetWay教授後來
It's a pity that he returned to Japan after retiring here
可惜他就是這邊退休之後回到日本
Died a few years later
後來沒幾年就過世
Before his death, there was a request from Dean Li Quan, Dean Li
生前然後還有李全院長 李院長院長的請託
Dr. Wu Shixiong established this foundation for scientific research and education in Taipei City, Taiwan
吳師兄博士成立台灣台北市的這個唐職科學研究教育的基金會
He is currently the chairman of the foundation to promote scientific research and education in Tang Dynasty
目前是他是任這個基金會董事長來推廣唐職科學研究及教育
So he has many high achievements in research and education
所以他在研究上面還有在教育上面都有很多很高的成就
Today he will share with us the relationship between Tang powder quality and life in the way of popular science
今天他會跟我們分享一下用科普的方式就是唐粉質更生命的關係
We welcome Dr. Wu
我們來歡迎吳博士
Thank you Vice President Li Wu for your introduction
謝謝李吳副院長的介紹
I have been in Academia Sinica for 43 years
我在中研院已經43年了
From the age of 65 this year, I entered the Institute of Biochemistry, Academia Sinica at the age of 22
從今年65歲我22歲進到中研院院生化所
At that time, the Institute of Biochemistry was at National Taiwan University.
那時候的生化所都在台大
until now i
一直到現在我
Frankly speaking, I started doing it as a graduate student.
坦白講就是從研究生開始做
slowly do it now
慢慢慢慢做做到現在
I will talk about this topic today
我今天講這個題目
The relationship between sugar molecules and life
糖質分子與生命的關係
I divide this part into four parts
我這一部分分成四大部分
As soon as I get to the first part, I'll cover the basic sugar
一到第一部分我會講基本的糖質
The second part will talk about the relationship between sugar and blood
那第二部分呢會講糖質跟血液的關係
Then the third part will talk about
然後第三部分呢就講
The relationship between sugar and infectious diseases
這個糖質跟傳染病的關係
The last part of the fourth part is about
第四部分最後一部分就講
our food
我們的食品
What does our healthy food have to do with sugar?
我們的健康食品跟糖質有什麼關係
Then I'm going to start with this sugary basic this one
那我現在就從這個糖質基本的這個
Let’s start with the basic chemical structure of sugar
糖質基本的這個化學結構開始來講
Our body is roughly divided into five categories
我們身體呢大概分成五大類
Materially speaking, we are really like eggs
我們物質來講真的像蛋
It is, of course, an enzyme
它主要當然就是一個酵素
Nucleic acid is genetic material
核酸就是遺傳物質
Our basic concept of sugar quality is
糖質我們大概基本的概念就是
it is an energy, an energy it provides
它是一個能量,它提供的一個能量
Fat is mainly related to cell membrane
脂肪它最主要跟細胞膜
Of course, there are many other functions, but they are more related to the cell membrane
當然還有很多功能,但是跟細胞膜比較有關係
Then there are minerals, inorganic minerals
再來就是礦物質,無機的礦物質
Like calcium, magnesium, mushrooms, scales, scales, these are in fact a coordinating agent
像鈣、鎂、菇、鱗、鱗,這些事實上是一個輔媒
Maybe these enzymes need these minerals to work
可能這些酵素在作用的時候需要有這些礦物質
Sugar is more than energy
糖質除了能量之外
When it is oxidized, it turns into carbon dioxide
它如果氧化之後,它就會變成二氧化碳
Produce ATP, we know that ATP is energy
產生ATP,我們知道ATP都是能源
and structure
還有結構
You can see the fiber of some plants
你可以看到有些植物的纖維質
It's just a structure, sugar, those fibers are sugar
它就是一個結構,糖,那些纖維都是糖
and chitins
還有幾丁子
The value of a few kilograms is actually a structure
幾斤值事實上也是結構
The value of a few catties is also the sugar value
幾斤值也是糖值
The third part is more complicated
那第三部分就比較複雜了
It can be used as a molecule for cell information transmission
它可以當成細胞信息傳遞的分子
cell-to-cell contact
細胞細胞之間的接觸
and your protein
還有你這個蛋白質
If you want to send to the synthesis
如果要送到合成完
where to send
要送到什麼地方
It also has to have sugar to boot it
它也必須要有糖來引導它
we say basic sugar
我們說最基本的糖
Regular sugar like this is the basic
像這樣普通糖是最基本
Its structure is that it's six carbons
它的結構就是它是六個碳
twelve hydrogen six oxygen
十二個氫六個氧
But here we call it six-carbon sugar
但是我們這邊叫做六碳糖
Of course there are five-carbon sugars and four-carbon sugars
當然糖還有五碳糖 四碳糖什麼
But our most basic
但是我們現在最基本的
just plain sugar
就是一個普通糖
it's one you see this first
它是一個你先看到這個
if it was a sugar
如果它是一個糖
it has a property
它有一個特性
One of the most important features is the
最重要的一個特性就是
it easily turns into sugar
它很容易容易變成糖
it has fat and protein
它跟脂肪跟蛋白
egg white some protein is also very easy to water
蛋白有些蛋白也很容易水
Some protein can also not easily water
有些蛋白也可以不容易水
like our hair is protein
像我們的頭髮就是蛋白
But our hair is not easy to water
但是我們頭髮就是不會容易水
what about glucose
那葡萄糖以外呢
and galactose
還有半乳糖
and glucosamine
還有葡萄糖胺
This is the OHG replaced by an amine group
就是這個 OHG被胺基取代
our name is glucosamine
我們叫葡萄糖胺
and some dried sucrose
還有一些就是乾鹿糖
a lot of salt algalose
鹽藻糖很多
Of course if there are some changes
那當然如果還有一些變化
It is this alcohol that will be oxidized to acid
就是這個醇內它會被氧化變成酸
That's of course glucosinolate
那當然就是葡萄糖全酸
no matter what
不管怎麼樣
Sugar has a very basic
糖有一個很基本的
It is itself at the first carbon
它本身就是在第一個碳
it's a whole acid
它就是一個全酸
We'll talk about this later
這個等一下我們會慢慢談
There are two types of sugar
那糖又分兩大類
Like if you look at glucose and fructose
像你如果看葡萄糖跟果糖
Fructose is much sweeter than glucose
果糖比葡萄糖甜很多
but in fact
但事實上呢
it is an isomer
它是一個同分異購物
clearly see this glucose
很清楚看到這個葡萄糖
It is a full machine
它就是有一個全機
its on the first carbon
它在第一個碳
it's the whole machine
它就是這個全機
what about fructose
那果糖呢
it's on the second carbon it's a copper
它在第二個碳它是個銅
so it's copper sugar
所以它是銅糖
That glucose is a whole sugar
那葡萄糖是一個全糖
the main difference
最主要的不同呢
Just in front of these two carbons
就在前面這兩個碳
Everything else is exactly the same
其他部位都完全一樣
that sugar itself
那糖本身
you can see it in the water solution
你可以看到它在水溶液裡面
We can draw it as beyond the chain
我們畫可以把它畫成指鍊之外
But what about in aqueous solution?
但在水溶液裡面呢
About ninety percent or more
大概百分之九十以上
it will ease
它會緩化
it will be more stable
它會比較穩定
You can see it slowing down, how to slow it down?
你可以看到它緩化,怎麼緩化呢?
It's on the fifth carbon, what about the fifth carbon, what about this
它在第五個碳,第五個碳呢,這個呢
will come to attack the second carbon and then become a slow
會來攻擊第二碳,然後變成一個緩壯的
This will be more stable
這個呢,就會比較穩定
When it becomes slow and strong, this one
當它變成緩壯之後呢,這一個
The first one is the first one, what about the carbon that has the authority?
第一個,就是第一個,這個有權機的這個碳呢
it will produce two solid shapes
它會有兩個立體形狀產生
You can see this OH this marked here
你可以看到這邊標示的這個 OH 這個
It can be pictured below, or it can be pictured above
有可以像下,也可以像上
This upward direction is what we call
這個向上呢,就是我們稱為
Upwards, we call it MEDA
向上呢,我們稱為MEDA
down, we call it α
向下呢,我們稱為α
This is mixed together, generally speaking
這個混在一起,一般來講呢
MEDA is relatively stable
MEDA比較穩定
So it is in the water, there will be more MEDA
所以它在水裡面,MEDA會比較多
What about this, remember this from now on
那這個呢,以後你們記住這個
As we'll see below, how important it is
下面就會講到,它到底有多重要
this you see how important it is
這個你看看它有多重要
let's see
我們來看
this is starch
這個是澱粉
Starch it is αe4
澱粉它就是αe4
That is, it is a giant sugar
也就是它是一個巨糖
It relies on αe4 such a direct
它是靠αe4這樣一直接
just saw this candy
就是剛剛看到這個糖
it this first oh it goes down
它這個第一個OH它往下
The gradual formation of sugars is two OH
糖漸的形成是兩個OH
take off a water
脫掉一個水
H2O leaves one sugar for two
H2O就留一個糖來兩個
leave an oxygen
留一個氧
oxygen hand
氧之手
Because oxygen is the hand of oxygen
因為氧本來就是氧之手
go pick up these two egg candies
去接這兩個蛋糖
That starch is αe4
那澱粉就是αe4
fiber is βe4
纖維就是βe4
In fact fiber and starch
事實上纖維跟澱粉
is the equivalent
是同分溢夠物
But its properties are completely different
但是它的物性完全都不一樣
Simply put, if we humans want to digest this starch, it is easy
簡單的講,我們人如果要消化這個澱粉,輕而易舉
But to digest fiber, it's not that hard
但是要消化纖維,那不很難
So generally speaking, if it is something alpha, it is probably easily digested in our stomachs
所以一般來講,如果是阿法的東西,我們在我們肚子裡面,大概很容易被消化掉
If you want fibers, you have to be like cows, horses, and sheep, which are anti-removal
如果要纖維呢,就要像牛啊,馬啊,羊啊,它是反除類的
It relies on the dimensional organisms in its four positions to decompose these fibers
它靠它四個位裡面的維生物去分解這些纖維質
But generally speaking, fiber, if it is, if it is Meta, Meta, it is more of a structural type
但是一般來講纖維質,如果是,如果是Meta,Meta的話呢,它比較是屬於結構型的
It belongs to the category. If Alpha is a food type, the score will be slightly lowered, but not absolutely.
比較屬於,如果是阿法是食物型的,大略降分,但是不是絕對這樣
Then I just said that sugar is our source of energy
那我剛剛講過糖就是我們能量的來源
What about us, if sugar, if glucose, a glucose, it will be broken down
我們呢,如果糖,如果葡萄糖,一個葡萄糖,它會被分解
decompose into red acid
先分解成餅紅酸
First decompose into two cake red acid
先分解成兩個餅紅酸
Cake red acid is to make three carbons
餅紅酸是讓三個碳
then come in
然後進來
if aerobic
如果有氧的情況之下
it produces a lot of
它會產生大量的
energy
能量
That is the process
也就是這個過程
is to be in
是要在
inside the body
力炫體裡面
do this
進行這種
under aerobic conditions
有氧的情況之下
If
如果說
when there is no oxygen
沒有氧的時候
if you go for a sun run
你如果去曬跑
Obviously I can't run anymore
明明呢跑不動了
no, because we probably
沒有,因為我們大概
eight minutes ahead
前面八分鐘
if you are a frequent runner
如果你常跑的人
about eight minutes ahead
前面大概八分鐘
about as much dextrose as you can use
大概你可以用的葡萄糖
run out
就耗盡了
It runs out in eight to ten minutes
八到十分鐘就耗盡了
not a player
不是選手
So if you usually run
所以一般跑的話
Then you want to run next
那你接下來你還想跑
but no way
但是沒辦法
Your oxygen, oxygen replacement, and other abilities are very poor
你的氧,代氧,各方面能力很不好
you run the next day
你隔天跑完
wow, that's a good deal
哇,這樣好算
It's because of lactic acid, lactic acid at the end
就是因為乳酸 乳酸到最後呢
will harden it from your blood into your liver
會從你的血液把它硬到肝裡面
Resynthesized into glucose and reused
再合成 變成葡萄糖再被利用
What about the other thing?
那另外呢 如果在維生物的
in the absence of oxygen
在無氧的情況之下呢
it carries on this put
它進行呢 這個 把
the fermentation that takes place, the fermentation results in alcohol
進行的發酵 發酵就會有酒精
Ah, if the control is not good
啊 如果控制不好
Alcohol is oxidized to acetic acid
酒精再氧化 就變成醋酸
For the longest time, it was a thin line away from acetic acid.
最久跟醋酸是一線之隔啦
what about the other one
那 另外一個呢
I said sugar can be turned into structure
我說 糖可以變成結構
The most obvious is
最明顯的呢 就是
Substance
基丁質
The so-called gelatin is derived from the original Xujing
所謂的基丁質是從原始的敘敬
until
一直到
crab until
螃蟹 一直到
crab shell shrimp shell insect
蟹殼 蝦殼 昆蟲
this appearance
這個外表
It's all base
都是基丁質
Butin is a polysaccharide
基丁質就是一種多糖
It is also VEDA
它也是VEDA
it is also
它也是
Relying on this VEDA 1 4 this way again and again
靠這個VEDA 1 4 這樣連 連 連
a linked polysaccharide
連起來的一個多糖體
What about the only thing that's different about him?
那他唯一不一樣的地方呢
He uses N and C glucosamine as a monomer
他是用N 以C葡萄糖胺當成單體
If it's fiber, he's using glucose
如果是纖維的話他是用葡萄糖
But this one uses N and C glucosamine as monomers
但是呢這個呢是用N 以C葡萄糖胺當成單體
This is what you eat if you eat veggie
這個呢如果你們吃維古力的話就是吃這個
I will talk about this later
這個我下面還會再講
So it can be used as a structure
所以他可以當成結構
So the link is of this Beta E4 is mainly like fiber and a few cents.
所以說這個Beta E4的 link is 主要像纖維啊幾丁值啊
it's all structure
這都是結構
There is one more concept I must convey to you first
還有一個概念我也必須先傳達給你們
That is to say, you, this candy, you keep directing you, your α E4 E keeps directing and directing
也就是說你這個糖你一直接你你α E4 E就一直接一直接
In fact he has his front and rear order
事實上他有他有前後秩序的
His 1, his first carbon is connected with his fourth carbon, connected together
他這個1,他的第一個碳跟他第四個碳接了,接在一起
For this, for this, his first carbon was originally
對這個,對這個來講呢,他第一個碳本來是
His first carbon would have had a full product
他第一個碳本來有一個全積
The whole product is oxidized, it becomes acid
全積被氧化,它變成酸
But, if you are a high school student, do you have any reaction now?
但是呢,如果高中生的話,現在有沒有做營進反應
If you have a reaction, do this
有營進反應的話,就是做這個
Is your sugar reducing sugar?
你這個糖是不是還原糖
What about this, this, this
那這個來講呢,這個,這個
What about the one on the right, the one on the left, it is
對右邊這個呢,左邊這個,它是
Disaccharides, the one on the left, we call them reducing sugars
雙糖嘛,左邊這個呢,我們稱為還原糖
It is because he is the first one, on the first carbon
就是因為他第一個呢,第一個碳上面
This is not used at all
這個全沒有被用掉
but this, this
那但是這個呢,這個
The one on the right and left is non-reducing sugar
右左邊這個呢,它是非還原糖
So if one is very long, the other is
所以你如果一個很長的,一個來講
it, if we re-transform, is on my right hand side
它,我們如果再化的話,就是我的右手邊
my right hand side
我的右手邊
is the restore side
就是還原端
The non-reducing end is always outside
非還原端永遠在外面
That
那
If enzymes break down sugar
酵素如果在分解糖的時候
it is uniform
它一律
almost uniform
幾乎一律
non-reducing
都是從非還原端
inward action
往內作用
non-reducing end
非還原端
Too
也是
closest outside
最接近外
close to the outermost
接近最外面的
wait a minute we will
等一下我們會
talk about this
談這個
sugar
糖
it's not that simple
它不是那麼單純
just a single
就是一個單
it can
它可以
correct
沒有錯
like starch
就像澱粉
like this chitin
就像這個幾丁籽
like fiber
就像纖維
it can aggregate
它可以聚合
become a polymer
成為一個聚合體
Polymer
聚合體
very long molecule
就很長很大的分子
just a glucose
就是一個葡萄糖
it can be straight
它可以一直接
It can be connected directly for a long time
直接可以接得很長
sugar
糖呢
it
它
can also
也可以
with fat
跟脂肪
glycolipid
形成了糖脂
the fat
這個脂肪
We know that if a candy
我們知道,如果是一個糖子
This molecule just becomes a very strange
這個分子就是變成一個很奇怪的
Because fat and sugar are incompatible
因為脂肪跟糖是很難相容的
One is clear water, fat
一個是清水性的,脂肪
It is polyhydric
這屬於聚水性的
So you can see the two words together
所以你可以看到這兩個在一起的話
You can see that this substance becomes a bisexual substance
你可以看到這個物質就變成兩性的物質
Some of it is clear water, and some of it is water
它有一部分是清水的,有一部分是劑水的
sorry, let me explain first
對不起,我先說明一下
because i'm not a philologist
因為我不是文字學家
Nine characters, you can see a lot here
九字,在這邊你可以看到很多
I use nine useful rice and I mix it up
我用九有用米,我混在一起
Because I think the two are about the same
因為我認為這兩個差不多
Some would argue that the two are not the same
有人會認為這兩個是不一樣
Some people say that you can also use the word "米" next to the things you fill in.
有人說你填的東西,他也可以用米字旁
For things not to be filled in, he can also use the word Nine
不填的東西,他也可以用九字旁
But I'm not a philologist
不過我不是文字學家
This may ask this to write text
這個可能要請教這個做文字的
text like the historical institute
像歷史研究所做文字
protein it can also form elastic
蛋白它也可以形成彈
Glycoprotein is very popular
糖蛋白 非常的熱門
What about our antibodies?
這個呢 我們的抗體
A lot of about 6-70% protein
很多大概6-70%以上的蛋白
are glycoproteins
都是屬於糖蛋白
I just said that after protein is modified with sugar,
我剛剛講過 蛋白被糖修飾之後
so that our cells know
它才能夠 我們細胞才知道
Which fixed organ should it be sent to?
要把它送到哪一個固定的器官裡面去
Okay, I'm going to look at this now. This is a basic
好 我現在來看 這個是一個基本的
The basic structure of the basic cell membrane
基本的細胞膜的基本的結構
Then you can see that this side is extracellular
那你可以看到這邊是細胞外
This is inside the cell
這邊是細胞內 這個呢
What is this sugar and fat?
這個糖脂肪它是怎麼樣
What about sugar and fat? Its fat part
糖脂肪呢 它的脂肪的部分
Just insert the whole thing on the membrane
就整個插在這個膜上面
It's exposed, it's a candy
它暴露出來呢 就是一個糖的
oligosaccharide or polysaccharide fraction
寡糖或多糖的部分
This one by one is sugar
這一顆一顆的這個就是糖
the outermost
那最外面的
Look at the outermost candy
你看這個最外面的這個糖呢
It is the non-reducing end
它就是非還原端
We are talking about the non-reducing end just mentioned
我們說的非還原端剛剛講過的
Then this is protein
那這個呢是蛋白
this protein
這個蛋白
What about this water-accumulating spiral?
這一個聚水性的螺旋呢
It permeates the entire cell membrane
它是整個灌穿整個細胞膜
Then the sugar part is also spread on the outside.
那這個糖的部分也都是鋪入在外面
Whether you are glycoprotein or purple Tibetan white
不管你是糖蛋白或是紫藏白
You are on the membrane like this oil slick
你在膜上面就是這樣浮油在
The so-called cell membrane
這個所謂的細胞膜上面
The cell membrane is of course formed by fat
那這個細胞膜當然就脂肪形成的
This is a picture of a microscope of a cell membrane
這個是一個細胞膜的一個顯微鏡的一個圖
you can see
你就可以看到
Its whiskers are glycolipids
它這個鬚鬚的部分呢就是糖脂
Then this black string
那這一個黑黑的這一串
This is inside the fat cell
這個是細胞脂細胞裡面
this whole
這一個整個呢
this is the cell membrane
這個是細胞膜
What about the hee hee hee part?
那這個嘻嘻嘻這個部分呢
sugar
就是糖質
every cell
每一個細胞
it
它
the appearance of these sugar
外表的這些糖
what does it represent
代表了什麼
represent our faces
就代表我們的臉
erythrocyte
紅血球
Will it be recycled in 190 to 120 days?
它一九十天到一百二十天會被回收嗎
then we
那我們
how does the body recognize
身體怎麼認說
This red blood cell is
這個紅血球是
old red blood cells
是老的紅血球
this is young
這個是年輕的
that is by
那就是靠
This on the outside of this cell
這個細胞外表的這個
this candy
這個糖來認
Cellular
還細胞的
sugar outside
外面的糖
with healthy cells
跟健康細胞的
The sugar outside is different
外面的糖是不一樣
old and young
老的跟年輕的
sugar outside
外面的糖
so i just said
所以我剛剛我說過
Glucose cost on the cell surface
細胞表面的糖質成本
different young
都不一樣年輕的
cells are different from brain cells
細胞跟腦細胞不一樣
sick cells vs healthy cells
生病的細胞跟健康的細胞
These sugars outside are not the same
外面這些糖質是不一樣
If the blue part of this picture is the protein
如果這個圖藍色的部分是蛋白
The yellow part is the sugar part
黃色的部分是糖的部位
you can see
你可以看到
The protein part is very tight
蛋白的部分是非常的緊密
won't move too much
也不會動很大
but the sugar part it can swing a lot
但是糖的部分它可以擺動的很大
That is, sugar molecules are easily fused with water.
也就是糖分子很容易跟水融在一起
Having this sugar may have a lot to do with this protein
有這個糖可能對這個蛋白起了很多的作用
protect it or many functions
保護它或者很多的功能
we'll talk about this later
這個我們等一下會談
So for a cell
所以對一個細胞
this is the nucleus
這個是細胞核
Those outside are sugar
那外面的這些呢就是糖
or protein
或者蛋白
That doesn't matter if your bacteria are coming
那不管你細菌要來
when attacking us
攻擊我們的時候
Sugar is the first thing
第一個碰到的就是糖
Viruses come and go
病毒要來也會碰到
first to sugar
第一個碰到糖
cancer cells to metastasize
癌細胞要轉移
he wants to transfer
轉移他也要
cut this off
把這個切斷
and then he was able to run
然後他才能夠跑
Or the cancer cells are going to go to a place
或者癌細胞要跑到一個地方
to protect
要護著
he also depends on this
他也要靠這個
sugar on top or
上面的糖或者
some protein and
一些蛋白跟
These surrounding cells interact with each other
這些周圍細胞互相
Contact him to be here
聯繫他才能夠在這邊
Implantation grows
著床壯大
become a cancerous tissue
變成一個癌組織
that or your hormones
那或者你的荷爾蒙
you want to touch
你要觸動
to stimulate
要來激發
to stimulate this cell
要來刺激這個細胞
met outside
外面碰到的
Possibly protein
也有可能就是蛋白
or sugar
或者糖
so
所以
what about this one
這一個呢
is typical
就是典型的就是
cell surface carbohydrate molecules
細胞表面的糖質分子
exchanging information with the outside world
是以外界交流信息
important bridge of
的重要的橋樑
Now what, I have to tell you about a protein
那現在呢 我必須要跟你們講一個蛋白
This protein is closely related to sugar
這個蛋白因為跟糖息息相關
lectin
這個蛋白我們稱為凝極素
What is lectin?
這什麼是凝極素呢
is that it is a protein
就是它是一個蛋白
It is a protein or glycoprotein that can bind with sugar
它是可以以糖質結合的蛋白 或糖蛋白
It can bind sugar
它可以跟糖質結合
When two cells come together
兩個細胞碰在一起的時候
lectin
互相都有凝極素
Lectin is a protein
凝極素是一種蛋白
But its function is to combine with sugar molecules
但是它的功能就是跟糖分子結合的
that's how it is
就是它怎麼這個
How does lectin combine with it
凝極素它怎麼跟它結合
like you see this
像你看到這個
cold virus
感冒病毒啊
Either weak energy or some poison
或者虛勁或者一些毒都有
I will give an example later
我等下會舉例子
Lectin is a protein
凝極素是一種蛋白
The function of this protein is to combine with sugar molecules
就是在這種蛋白的功能就是跟糖分子會結合在一起
Thanks
謝謝
But the power of this spirit number combined with sugar molecules
但是這個靈體數跟糖分子結合的力量
It's combined, this power is not going through the carpool
它結合在一起,這個力量不是經過共駕艦
That's what we call, it's a second class ship
也就是我們所說的,它是經過二級艦
That's the power you can't see
也就是你看不到的力量
you can measure it, but sometimes
你可以測的到,但是有時候
You're probably thinking it's not a real chemical ship
你們大概就想成它不是真正的化學艦
Is it a clear ship or an ion ship
它是有清艦或者離子艦
or ring de valli , or the effect of polyhydricity
或者環德瓦利,或者聚水性的作用
Paste together, it will produce two and combine together
貼在一起,就會產生兩個就結合在一起
This power is not very strong, but
這個力量不是很強,但是
Phenomena that have dominated our lives since the Lord
主以來主導我們生命的現象
Both of these tell us that the combination of the number of spirits and sugar molecules
這兩個都告訴我們,靈體數跟糖分子的結合
Relying on the power of this non-common ship
就是靠著這個非共駕艦的力量
Kiyomi, positive and negative electricity attract together
清見 正負電 吸引在一起
what about this you can see
這個呢 你可以看到
When a virus wants to enter our cells
當病毒要進到我們細胞的時候
There are some lectin on the virus
病毒上面有一些凝極素
can bind to cellular sugars
可以跟細胞的糖結合
Or the cholera toxin
或者呢 霍亂的毒素
when it enters our cells
它要進到我們細胞的時候呢
What about the toxin?
這個毒素呢
it also passes through
它也要透過
sugar that will stick to the cell first
也會先黏在這個細胞上面的糖
or germs
或者病菌
Lactobacillus
像令龍感菌
it has a lot of this lectin
它有很多這個凝極素
It will also deactivate the lectin on the bacteria
它也會先這個細菌上面的凝極素
will bind to this sugar on our cells
會跟這個我們細胞上面的糖結合
and then into our cells
然後就進到我們的細胞裡面
sometimes like the most famous
那有的時候像最有名的
like white blood cells
像白血球
it's going to where we hurt
它要跑到我們受傷的地方
escape from the blood vessels
從維血管跑出來
what about this time
這個時候呢
How does it focus on vascular
它怎麼樣專注維血管
The first step also relies on lectin
第一步也是靠著凝極素
It's the urgency number on the maintenance tube that attracts it down
就是維協管管閉上面的凝急數把它吸引下來
Then he'll run out to the injured area to fight the foreign intrusion
然後他就會跑出去到受傷的地方來對抗外來侵入的東西
In fact, these are all related to our life and life.
這些事實上都是跟我們的生活、生命都有關係
Therefore, it will be easier to talk about the following after the anxious number is finished.
所以凝急數講完之後講下面就會比較容易
In order to let everyone have a better understanding of the number of jitters, let me give you an example
為了要讓大家對凝急數有一個了解 我舉一個例子
Let me give you an example golden boar protein
我舉一個例子 金牡豬蛋白
Have you heard of golden boar protein? This is our academician Lin Rongrong who has done a lot of research
金牡豬蛋白聽過嗎?這個是我們林榮耀院士做了很多研究
Golden boar protein is quite poisonous
金牡豬蛋白是蠻毒的
I remember playing with this a lot when I was a kid and its seeds
我記得我小時候經常玩這個 它的種子
But it's actually quite poisonous in it
但事實上它裡面是很毒的
It has a kind of what we call golden boar protein in it
它裡面有一種 有我們說金牡豬蛋白
it has two
它有兩個
Divide it into two parts, you see, it finances into the egg white and divides it into two parts
分成兩部分,你看到,它金融入蛋白分成兩部分
Part of it, let's say A, part of it
一部分呢,我們說A,一部分
Let's call this blue A
這藍色我們叫A好了
Let's call the part of this potential color B.
這個潛力色的部分我們叫B好了
A what is it? A is actually an enzyme
A它是什麼?A事實上是一個酵素
it goes into
它進到
If it enters our cells, it will put
它如果進到我們細胞裡面,它會把
protein-making machine, glycosome, inside
製造蛋白的機器,合糖體,裡面的
RNA breaks it down
RNA把它分解掉
It's quite a lot, but what if
它是相當多,但是呢,如果
only A, if you owe
僅僅只有A,欠的話
only A words
只有A的話
don't read it because it can't get into the cell
都不讀,因為它進不了細胞
In fact there are many plants that only contain A
事實上有很多植物,只有含有A
but not toxic
但是沒有毒性
It depends on B, what is B?
它要靠的B,B是什麼呢?
B is that it is a lectin
B是它是一個凝極素
A and B are connected by double arrows
A跟B是用雙流箭連在一起
B it will look for sugar on the cell surface
B它會找細胞表面的糖質
At once
就
He is Ningji Sutu, after he combines with him
他是凝脊宿退,他跟他結合之後
If it is beneficial to A, enter
有利於A就進到
just go to this
就進到這個
enters the cells and becomes very toxic
進到細胞裡面,然後就變得很毒
This financial strain is actually very similar to that coin toxin
這個金融株彈柏事實上跟那個幣麻毒素是很類似的
One of the most famous cases was in 1978 when
最有名的一個案例就是在1978年的時候
A reporter from Eastern Europe lived after he escaped
東歐的一個記者他是逃出來之後呢在
The British national broadcaster BBC is a reporter who has been bashing
英國的國家廣播公司BBC當記者他是一直抨擊
Bulgaria slams this Russia
保家利亞抨擊這個俄羅斯
Russia's KGB
俄羅斯的KGB就
use this toxin
用這個毒素
put it on top of this umbrella
放在這個雨傘上面
Inject it into this guy while riding the subway
在搭捷運的時候把它注射到這個人
At first he didn't know why he just said it was crowded
最初他不知道為什麼他只是說很擠碰到一下
What about the toxin?
事實上這毒素呢
very fine
很精細的
Put it in a small iron ball
放在一個小小的鐵球裡面呢
Just like that, after four days, he died
就這樣子,過了四天之後,他就死掉
So this thing is actually very poisonous
所以這個東西,事實上是非常的毒
So I front these
所以我前面這些
I'm done with the basics
基本的我講完了
I'm going in now
我現在要進入呢
I hope you will be more interested
我希望大家會更有興趣的
What I'm going to talk about next is related to academics
下面我講的是跟學藝有關的
some stories
一些堂子的故事
bloody
血腥
There are mud blood, hematopoiesis, diabetes disease
還有泥血、造血、糖藥病
the blood
這些血液
these stories
這些故事
you see blood
你看到血腥
bloody
血腥
If before 1900
如果在1900年之前
No one knows there is type A and there is type AB
沒有人知道有A型,有AB型
O type
有O型
Why
為什麼
will find out
會發現呢
It's someone who survived a blood transfusion
就是有人呢,輸血活了
Someone got a blood transfusion and died from the same blood transfusion
有人輸血,同樣輸血死掉了
don't know
搞不清楚
1900, 24 seasons ago
1900年也就是24季之前
No one knows there is type A, there is type B, there is type AB, there is type O
根本沒有人知道有A型 有B型 有AB型 有O型
But what about the blood type here?
但是呢 這邊血型呢 它的
It is formed on the surface of red blood cells
它是由紅血球表面
This is a red blood cell.
這個是個紅血球好了
Glucose antigens on the surface to determine what blood type you are
表面的糖質抗原來決定你是什麼血型的
you can see type o
你們可以看到O型
What about type O?
O型呢 它的
Glycoantigen here
糖質抗原在這裡
Type A, there is one more
A型呢 多了一個
This quadrangular one is called galactosamine
這個四角型的 這個叫半乳糖胺
one extra
多了一個
so you type a
所以你A型
What about blood type A?
A型的這個血型呢
What about the antigen?
這個抗原呢
O type no
O型沒有
What about type O antigens?
O型的抗原呢
Look at 1234, this type A is in the process of synthesis
你看1234 這個A型在合成的過程
There will also be O-type
也會有O型的
So you type O lose to type A
所以你O型輸給A型
no problem
沒有問題
Type A
A型
Type O you lose to Type A
O型你輸給A型
Does a person with type A have type O antigens?
A型的人他有O型的抗原嗎
Type A and Type B cannot belong to each other.
那A型跟B型不能互相屬
Because type B has one more galactose than type O
因為B型他比O型多了一個半乳糖
In fact, type A and type B
事實上A型跟B型
one more galactose
一個多了一個半乳糖
one is galactose
一個是半乳糖
but this one is different
但這個呢哪裡不一樣
It’s just that the position where I painted Lanlan is different
就是我畫藍藍的這個位置不一樣
It's just that the location is different
就是這個位置不一樣
such a small difference
就這麼微細的差別
You type A can't lose to type B
你A型就不能輸給B型
Type B can't lose to Type A
B型也不能輸給A型
because it's what you typed in
因為它是你輸進去的話
it treats it as a foreign object
它會把它當成一個外來物
Such a large amount of foreign matter comes in
這麼大量的外來物進來
that's worth it
那還得了
That person will probably be carbon off.
那人大概就會碳掉了
So the blood transfusion was wrong
所以輸血輸錯了
will die
就會死掉
But type AB, he has both
但是AB型呢他兩個都有
Type AB, he also has type A
AB型呢他A型的他也有
Type B he also has
B型的他也有
Galactose also has
半乳糖也有
What about this, so you type A lose to type AB
那這個呢所以你A型輸給AB型
There is no problem losing to the AV type
輸給AV型都沒有問題
it's all acceptable
它都可以接受
So this is easy to see
所以這個就很容易看到
You type O can lose to any type
你O型可以輸給任何一型
But Type A except itself
但是A型除了它自己以外
It can also only lose to the AV type
它也只能輸給AV型
it can't lose to type a either
它也不能輸給A型
Can't lose to V-type
也不能輸給V型
Like the V-type, it can't lose to the O-type
V型一樣它也不能輸給O型
Can't lose to Type A
也不能輸給A型
But it can lose to AV type
但是它可以輸給AV型
AV type can
AV型都可以
But its main difference
但它這個最主要差別
i just said
我剛剛講過
It is the surface of the red snowball
就是紅雪球表面
Glycoantigens to determine your studies
糖質抗原來決定你的學習
then you will see in
那你會看到在
There was an article in 2007
2007年有一篇文章
a biotech company
有一個生技公司
Did he say it was easy?
他說那很簡單嗎
I put an enzyme
我就放一個酵素
Cut off the A-type
把A型的這個切掉
AV type this cut off
AV型這個切掉
Let's cut it all together and make it all O-shaped
一起來切掉 全部都變成O型
someone did it
這有人做
He cut it off with enzymes and all the blood became type O
他用酵素把它切掉 所有的血都變成O型
It's very simple.
很簡單 這樣子的話就
It's fine if you lose
就輸了就好了 這個呢
It was in 2007
是在2007年的時候
There is an article in Nature about Technology
有一篇文章呢 他在Nature about Technology
In this journal, he mentioned that
這個期刊裡面 他有講到這樣
This is also a kind of biotechnology
這個也是生物科技的一種
Sometimes when there is a blood shortage
有時候血荒的時候呢
You can't find this with this blood type
你找不到這個血型的這個
They are all type B, so what should I do?
都是B型的 那怎麼辦
You're also type B, you can't lose to him
你也B型 你也不能輸給他
You can lose to him, but you can't lose to him
也可以輸給他 但是也不能輸給他
At this time, take an enzyme and cut this off
這時候拿個酵素把這個切掉
It's very simple to say, but it should be built with a lot of technology
講很簡單 這個做應該是建設到很多技術
Okay, we're done with blood types, let's talk about this again.
好 血型講完了 我們再來講這個
red blood cell count
紅血球生成數
What about red blood cell count?
紅血球生成數呢
this initial poetic
這 initial poetic
Let's call it epo for short.
我們簡稱叫epo好了
Chinese is called red blood cell production number
中文就叫紅血球生成數
what about this epo
那這個epo呢
what is
是甚麼
because of U.S
因為我們
if blood stem cells
如果是血液幹細胞
blood stem cells
血液幹細胞的話
it differentiates into red blood cells
它要分化成紅血球
or it differentiates into white blood cells
或者它要分化成白血球
or differentiate into platelets
或者分化成血小板
have to go through hormones
都必須要經過激素
specific hormone destimulation
特定的激素去刺激
specific hormone
特定的激素
then if it goes through
那如果它經過
If blood stem cells
如果血液的幹細胞
in our bones
在我們的骨髓裡面
after release
釋放出來之後
If by this epo
如果被這個epo
red blood cell production
就是紅血球生成數
after stimulation it will
刺激之後它就會
differentiate into red blood cells
分化成紅血球
what about this
那這個呢
What about the red blood cell count?
這個紅血球生成數呢
where is it produced
在哪邊產生
mostly in our kidneys
大部分在我們的腎臟
Produced in renal myocytes
腎肌胞裡面產生
Dialysis person
洗腎的人
would not be able to generate enough
就沒辦法產生足夠量的
epo blood
epo這種血
So what about people who wash their kidneys?
所以洗腎的人呢
he will be very
他會很
very weak very tired
很弱 很累
Because he doesn't have enough red blood cells, he's anemic.
因為他的紅血球不夠 他貧血
anything else
還有呢
this
這個
In fact there is something like this
事實上還有就是像這個
If the retarded man uses
這個愛滯病犯 如果他用
He will also be anemic with medication
用藥 他也會貧血
that is
也就是
not enough red blood cells
紅血球不夠
at this time
那這時候
In this epo in 1989, he
在1989年的這個epo呢 他就
by US drug
被美國藥物
What about the Food Administration, he will approve
食品管理局呢 他就核准
You can come and wash this kidney
可以來給這個洗腎的人
to make him
為了讓他
be able to have enough of this
能夠有足夠量的這個
This red blood cell, so I injected this
這個紅血球 所以就注射了這個
very good effect
效果非常的好
So let me see below
所以我下面來看
he actually
他事實上呢
Epo is a glycoprotein
Epo他是一個糖蛋白
green part
綠色的部分
you will see the green part
你會看到綠色的部分呢
just a protein
就是一個蛋白
the colored part
有顏色的這個部分
he has four
他有四
he has four candies
他有四條糖
This one this one is sugar
這一個一個這個就是糖
sugar chain sugar chain
糖鏈糖鏈
so he is a glycoprotein
所以他是一個糖蛋白
he has four candies
他有四條的糖
those candies
那這些糖
if
如果
Our First Generation Biotechnology
我們第一代的生物科技
produced
產生出來的
just without sugar
就是沒有糖的
What about this Epo without sugar?
這個沒有糖的這個Epo呢
Hit the human body?
打到人體呢
Useless
沒有用
But what about in the lab if you use cells
但是呢在實驗室如果你用細胞
It can work without hitting the human body
不打到人體是可以作用的
What does this mean?
這表示呢
sugar
糖
these sweeteners
這些糖劑
is protecting the protein
是在保護這個蛋白
That is, if you don't have these sweeteners
也就是你如果沒有這些糖劑
protect this outside
在外面保護這個
Protein, Epo protein, when it hits the human body
蛋白,Epo這個蛋白,打到人體的時候
It is easily broken down in the blood
它就很容易在血液裡面可能就被分解掉
So Epo has glycoprotein
所以Epo它是有糖蛋白
The stability of this sugar in the human body is related to
在人體裡面這個糖劑,它的穩定性是有關的
There is a big biotechnology company in the United States called MGN
美國有一家現在的生技大廠,叫做MGN
It produced Epo, and because of Epo, it turned a large group
它就生產了Epo,因為Epo而轉的很大團
Become a big factory of biotechnology
變成生技的一個大廠
In fact, the conversion of the Epo gene was done by Taiwanese Lin Fukun
事實上Epo基因的轉值是由台灣人林福坤來完成的
I checked his, actually from 1975 to 1977
我查他的,事實上在1975年到1977年
All jobs at this hospital
在本院的職位所有工作
Epo has another story
Epo還有另外一個故事
He was in the Blood Olympics in 2000
他在2000年的時候血液奧運
declared banned
被宣佈是禁藥
Because the players need to bring more oxygen
因為選手為了要帶多一點氧氣
so many people hit
所以很多人就打
just hit a wave
就打一波
Playing a wave has promoted a lot
打一波促進了很多
He has more red blood cells than you
他這個紅血球含量比你還多
I can run faster than you
我就跑得比你還快
because i have oxygen
因為我帶氧
he will run faster than you
他就會跑得比你還快
so why ban him
那為什麼要禁他呢
very dangerous
非常危險
What we people strive for is a balance
我們人講求的是一個平衡
when you have too many red blood cells
當你紅血球過多的時候
will cause blood
就會造成血液
high viscosity
黏稠度高
Stickier
黏比較黏
then you'll break your heart
那你就會破死你的心臟
compression
壓縮
you a thing
你一個東西
your blood is stickier
你血液比較黏
your heart's last strength of course
你當然心臟的最後力
will increase
就會比較加大
So some players get killed
所以有選手觸死
It's because of a heart attack that will kill you
就是因為心臟病會觸死
So what about social technology?
所以社會科技呢
can be used to save you
可以用在救你
can hurt you too
也可以在害你
Technology is always neutral
科技永遠是中性的
Next, let me say that it is also a kind of sugar-based medicine.
下面呢我講也是一種糖質的一個藥
But this glycin is actually an anti-coagulation problem naturally produced in our body
但是呢這個甘素事實上是我們體內天然產生的一個抗凝血的一個問題
have you ever donated blood
你們有沒有捐過血
What if your blood won't clot when you go to donate blood?
如果你們去捐血的時候發現你的血不會凝固嗎
Blood generally clots when it leaves the body
如果血離開身體一般來講是會凝固的
If your blood leaves your body or yours then you have blood disease
如果你的血離開身體或者你的那那你就是血有病啊
your blood does not coagulate
你的血不凝固
What about when you go to donate blood?
那你去捐血的時候呢
Anticoagulant blood will be put in the blood bag
那個血袋裡面呢就會放抗凝血
For anticoagulation, there may be two types
抗凝血呢它就有可能有兩種
Sometimes it puts a citric acid
有的時候呢它是放了一個檸檬酸
lower your pH
把你的PH值降下來
glucosinolate
有的就是放甘素
it's a sugar glycine in fact
它是一個糖 甘素事實上
Glucose is actually a sugar
甘素事實上是一個糖
It is a natural aggregation of this
它是一種天然的這個聚合
is that it relies on sour sugar
就是它是靠酸糖
A lot of sour sugar combined like this
很多酸糖這樣結合起來
a long long molecule
一個很長很長的一個分子
a sugar molecule
一個糖分子
it can be used to treat
它可以用來治療
if you have surgery
你如果有開刀
Deeper blood acid
比較深的進賣血酸
The lungs also have blood acid, arterial acid, etc.
肺也會血酸 動脈血酸這些
and myocardial infarction
還有心肌梗塞
Because myocardial infarction is also the main
因為心肌梗塞也是主塞
But when glycin itself is used
但是甘素本身用的時候
There are two most feared side effects
最怕副作用有兩個
If the amount used is difficult to control
一個用的量很難控制的話
it causes internal bleeding
它就會造成內出血
or your blood is harder to clot
或者你血液比較難凝固
Platelet function will decrease
血小板功能會下降
This has happened to many
這個在很多來講也出過事
I know mainland China is separated from pigs or cows
我知道中國大陸是從豬或牛分離出來
That is also used in the human body in Gansu
那個也的甘肅用在人的身體
that happened too
那也出過事
How Gansu works
甘肅是怎麼樣作用
make it blood anticoagulant
讓它血液抗凝血
It is so anticoagulant in nature
是這樣抗凝血在天然裡面
we can find out
我們就可以發現
mosquitoes draw your blood
蚊子吸引你的血
If you go to fight mosquitoes
你去打蚊子的話
bloody hands
滿手是血
Mosquitoes have their own anticoagulants
蚊子本身就有抗凝血
draw your blood
吸引你的血
The water quality is also in the attraction
水質也一樣在吸引裡面
In fact, many
這個事實上很多都
The mechanism of this protocol is actually a series of hydrolysis reactions of protein berry
這個協議零顧的機制事實上是一連串的蛋白莓的水解反應
These meringues are zero blood factor
這些蛋白莓都是零血因子
Protocols that lack either one may not be able to zero
缺少任何一個的協議都可能沒辦法零顧
If you can't zero in on which one are you missing?
如果你沒辦法零顧你缺少了哪一個呢
Then if you lack it, there is no way for Zero Gu to become blood sick.
那你缺少了沒辦法零顧就有可能變成血有病嘛
What about Gansu, its mechanism is that our human body has a protein
那甘素呢它的機制是我們人體有一種蛋白
I'm sorry, I don't know how to do this. I want to translate on my own, but I can't.
這個對不起我不會我自主想要翻譯但沒辦法翻譯
It is called antiso-min
它這個就叫做antiso-min
by itself if alone
它本身如果單獨的話
It can be combined with this factor10A this can be combined with it
它可以跟這個factor10A這個可以跟它結合
But it is relatively weak, but once this protein is combined with glycin
但是比較弱但是一旦這個蛋白它如果有甘素跟它結合的話
It can be combined with this factor10
它跟這個factor10可以結合
become a hundred times stronger
就變成上百倍的力量
Increase the binding force hundreds of times
增加上百倍的結合力
So it's possible to block this
所以就可能阻止了這個
Block this cascade of protein berry hydrolysis reactions
阻止這一連串的蛋白莓的水解反應
So it can turn blood into Naya Gu
所以它就可以把血變成波綾顧
The most efficient one right now is
現在最有效的一個就是
The most effective is these five candies
最有效的就是這五顆糖
The name of these five candies
這五顆糖的這個名字
I can't find the Chinese name
我也找不到中文名字
terribly sorry
非常抱歉
called fandopalinex
叫做fandopalinex
It is a very strong anti-bleeding agent
它是非常強的一個抗淩血劑
Vice President Liu just said that
剛剛劉副院長有講到就是說
There are many sugar quality experts in our Chinese Academy
我們中文院有很多糖質的專家
Director of Genome Center
現在基因體中心的主任
red top
紅上層
Director Hong is actually
紅主任事實上就是
it has
它有
he studies this one
他研究這一個
this one
這一個
This substance of the five halls
五個堂的這個物質
He studies its synthesis
他研究它的合成
Research
研究的
It seems that there are many patents
好像有很多專利
It seems that they are planning to start a company to do this.
好像也準備開公司來做這個
In fact this thing
事實上這一個東西
it can replace dry element
它可以取代乾素
Then what
然後呢
If you after surgery
你如果手術之後
cause arterial thrombosis
引起動脈 血栓 血塞
it can be clear
它可以清楚
Then for acute coronary
然後對於急性的冠狀動脈
It is better than traditional dry vegetarian
它是比傳統的乾素更好
this
這個
It is a very important medicine
算起來是很重要的一個藥
now everyone wants to make it
現在大家都想把它
synthesized
合成出來
Then you can use many
然後就可以用到很多
not just medicine
不只是藥
Then when you donate blood, you can also put some
那你捐血的時候也可以放一點
ok let's see now
好 我們現在來看
Diabetes mellitus this generation is also more
糖藥病這代也比較
My blood sugar is also relatively high, so I pay more attention to this
我的血糖也比較高啦 所以我對這個也比較注意
This diabetes disease is really scary
這糖藥病真的非常恐怖
Will your eyes be blind? Will your kidneys be damaged?
大家眼睛會瞎嘛 腎臟會壞嘛
high blood sugar
他糖藥病血糖高
Why is it hurting so much? He hit all of this.
怎麼這麼傷身啊 他是打在所有的這個
Organ why?
器官啊 為什麼
I just said he's a circular and straight lover
我剛剛講過 他是一個環狀跟直戀狀
Straight love has a punch on it as long as there's a punch
直戀狀上面有一個拳 只要有拳擊在
This is protein
這個算是蛋白 蛋白有
If there is an amino group, he will box with the amino group.
有胺基 他就拳擊跟胺基
it's easy to become a suction test
就很容易變成吸乎檢
Just call up, it's okay to check
就打上來 這吸乎檢可以
It's delicious, but it sucks if
是可膩的 但是吸乎檢如果
If it takes a long time, he will become a non-greasy, non-greasy word
久的話他就會變成不可膩 不可膩的話
What about the glycoprotein?
那這個糖蛋蛋白呢
It will be elasticized. If it is elasticized too much, it will gradually lose its function.
就會被彈化 彈化多了呢 就漸漸失去功能
Eyes will go blind if you drink
眼睛會瞎 你如果喝
Drink A wine, you drink A wine, drink methanol
喝甲酒,你喝甲酒,喝到甲醇
Methanol becomes methanol in our body
甲醇在我們人體就會變成甲醇
You drink, you alcohol, it's alcohol, it's okay
你喝,你醇,就是酒精,沒事
It's okay to drink methanol
喝甲醇就有事
That's because, Yichun
就是因為呢,儀醇呢
It can always be oxidized to acid
它可以一直氧化變成儀酸
But methanol can only be oxidized to methanol
但是甲醇呢,只能氧化到甲醇
Methanol is so poisonous, why?
甲醇這麼毒啊,為什麼?
Because it is the total product
因為它是全積啊
With full product, you can beat any egg white
全積呢,就可以打任何的一個蛋白
So drink alcohol, methanol, you will go blind
所以喝到甲酒,甲醇,你會眼睛瞎掉
That's the whole problem
也就是全的問題
Methanol, mainly the total product
甲醇這個,主要有全積
so you can see
所以你可以看到
If diabetes is sick, because we human beings
如果糖藥病,因為我們人
I just talked about protein, it has a certain
我剛剛講過蛋白呢,它有一定的
If your protein is old, it will be recycled
你如果蛋白老了,它就會回收
If your protein recovery rate is greater than
如果你蛋白的回收再生率大於
Destruction rate Your protein will be destroyed
破壞率 你這個蛋白會被破壞
Then you are normal, you are normal
那你就是正常人嘛 你就正常啊
But what if you get sick from diabetes?
但是呢 你如果呢 如果糖藥病的呢
Because of you, your destruction rate
因為你 你這個破壞率
bigger than this
大於這個
recycling rate that
回收再生率 那
then you just
那你就
no way, you are
沒辦法嘛 你就是
like us at my age
像我們 像我這種年紀
if compared with younger
如果跟年輕的比
My Protein Recovery Rate
我的蛋白回收再生率
far inferior to you young man is
遠遠比不上你 年輕人就是
All aspects of him are comparisons
他的各方面就是比較
Recycling rate, regeneration
回收率啊再生啊
This recycle we all
這個recycle 我們所
The so-called recycle is stronger
所謂的這個recycle 他就是比較強
well there like
好 有 像
Medication for type 2 diabetes like these
第二型糖藥病的用藥裡面像這些
This drug is of course a sugar molecule.
這個藥呢 當然也是糖質分子啦
He is the will to decompose the beauty of starch
他就是把澱粉分解美的意志掉
It's all about decomposing starch
都是 都是把澱粉的分解美
just suppress it
就把它抑制掉
Now we break down the brow is what we call
現在我們分解眉就是我們所謂的
Alpha Valley Sides
阿法谷國賽德斯
so suppress it
這樣就把它抑制掉
what about this
這個呢
Most of this medicine is what you eat
這種藥大部分都是你吃飯
food money
吃飯的錢
eat in a few minutes
幾分鐘先吃了
So the medication for type 2 diabetes
所以第二型糖藥病的用藥
some are also
有一些也都是
molecules of sugar
是糖子的分子
Okay, so now I'm going to tell you a story about this infectious disease.
好那我現在講這個傳染病有關的故事
Infectious diseases are actually the same in all countries
傳染病事實上各國都一樣
Encountered an infectious disease
碰到傳染病
The policy of the first country is like this
第一個各國的政策都是這樣
The most important thing to fight is the cold
最要對抗的就是感冒
The first one was terrible because of the cold
第一個因為感冒太恐怖了
historically horrible
從歷史上太恐怖了
let's see
我們來看看
this is in
這個呢是在
This picture happened in the United States in 1918
這個圖呢是在美國發生在1918年
just the first time
正好是第一次
when the world war is coming to an end
世界大戰要結束的時候
Spanish tourism at this time
這時候西班牙旅遊感
Invasion of the world is in the hands of the United States
侵襲全球在美國手上其中
this time
這個當時
Hospitals, businesses, cities are all infected
醫院、經營、城市全部都被感染
So at that time
所以當時呢
It was March 1918
是1918年3月
This sense of tourism but living in the United States to see women's health in Saz State
這個旅遊感卻住在美國的看薩茲州女衛生發生
Then slowly expand to every corner of the world
然後慢慢擴展到世界每一個角落
At that time from March 1918 until June 1920
那時候從1918年3月一直到1920年6月
I don't know why it disappeared
發生消失原因都不知道
But at least 20 million people died
但是至少死了2000萬人
this is horrible
這個是太恐怖了
Some even say hundreds of millions
甚至有人說上億
close to 100 million
要接近1億
At that time, medical technology was not so advanced.
那時候的真的醫療科技沒有那麼發達
But back then, people's brains were pretty powerful.
但是那時候人的腦筋也蠻厲害的
He used the patient's specimen with spicy
他把病人的檢體用辣
Crazy save
瘋存
After hot crazy save
辣瘋存之後
So, in 2004, scientists reconstructed this flu virus
所以呢他在2004年科學家就把這個流感病毒重建了
Proved he was a H1N1 flu
證明了他是一個H1N1的流感
I'm going to talk about what is H and what is N
我要講的是什麼是H什麼是N
I saw it in your report.
你那報索上都有看到啊
HN H1N1 what is H what is N
HN H1N1什麼是H什麼是N
I'm going to talk to you about this now
現在就要跟大家談這個問題
What is H?
什麼是H呢
H is sialyl lectin
H是唾液酸凝極素
Its name is Hemagutinin
它的名字就叫Hemagutinin
it is a lectin is a protein
它是一個凝極素是一個蛋白
is a protein on the surface of cold viruses
是在感冒病毒表面的一個蛋白
N is sialidohydrolase
N是唾液酸水解酶
its a beer sugar
它是一個啤酒的糖
beer is sugar with beer
啤酒是有啤酒的糖
The acid is almost gone forever, forever at the ring end of the flying ring
脫衣酸永遠幾乎了 永遠在飛環圓端
That is, the outermost part of the cell sugar
也就是細胞糖的最外面
So when the lectin of the virus suddenly ran to our respiratory tract
所以當病毒這個凝結素一下子跑到我們的呼吸道這邊
The first thing that happened was he went to the stripper again and glued it on
第一個碰到就是他又去找脫衣上 把它黏上去
So stick it on, this is the first step for the cold virus to enter the cell
所以黏上去 這個是感冒病毒進入細胞的第一步
It's a lectin. As I just said, lectin can bind to sugar.
它是一個凝結素 我剛剛講過 凝結素是跟糖可以結合
It's going to find it, it's a protein, it's in the cold virus
它就會去找 它是一個蛋白 是在感冒病毒
These are proteins on the outside of the cold virus and genetic material on the inside
感冒病毒外面這些都是蛋白 裡面是遺傳物質
Its genetic material is RNA not DNA it is RNA
它的遺傳物質RNA 不是DNA 是RNA
Outside, there are two very important proteins
外面呢 有兩種很重要的蛋白
One is H which is the lectin of dehydrating acid
一個是H 就是脫液酸的凝結素
one is N
一個是N
N is a dehydrating acid hydrolase
N就是一個脫液酸水解酶
This is the H?
這個呢 是要 這個H呢
This protein is used to enter cells
這個蛋白呢 是要進入細胞用的
The N is to leave the virus after soaking into the cells
這個N呢 是要離開病毒泡到細胞之後
After copying, when it is about to leave
複製 複製完 它要離開的時候呢
Use N to cut off the dehydrating acid
就要用N 把這個脫液酸切掉
Cut off the dehydrating acid it's of course fine
把脫液酸切掉 它當然很好
Otherwise, I'll tell you later
不然的話 等一下我會跟大家講
What is the use of this and what is the use of these two
這個 它的用途在哪裡 這兩個的用途在哪裡
This is dehydrating acid
這個是脫液酸
What about dehydrating acid? I just talked about it.
脫液酸呢 我剛剛講的
Glycolipid molecules usually on the outside of cells
通常在細胞外面的糖脂分子
And it's at the reducing end of the lung, which is the outermost
而且是在肺還原端 也就是最外面
So what about cold viruses like ours
所以呢 感冒病毒 像我們這個
Cold virus comes from our respiratory tract
感冒病毒來 就是我們的呼吸道
nose, this, this
鼻子啊 這個這個
as soon as it comes
它一來 就
Check for dehydrating acid, if there is, it sticks
看看有沒有脫液酸 有的話它就黏上去了
ok look at this picture
好 你看看這個圖
When this H, there are a lot of H outside, this is a virus.
當這個H 這個外面有很多H 這個是病毒好了
What about the virus, it found us, this, this is a human cell
病毒呢 它找到我們 這個這個是人的細胞
Viruses are of course much smaller than human cells
病毒呢 跟人的細胞比當然它是小的很多
But it's the first one, it's attached to this dehydrating acid
但是它第一個呢 就接在這個脫液酸上面
It's attached to this dehydrating acid. Look for it.
它接在這個脫液酸上面 它找找找找
Then it slowly enters our cells
然後呢 再慢慢的進到我們細胞裡面
When it enters the cell, it controls our entire cell
當它進到細胞裡面呢 它就會控制我們整個細胞
Tell our cells to do a lot of confinement of this cold virus
叫我們的細胞做很多這個感冒病毒的圍力
It will do a lot, become controlled by it, and do it all
它就會做很多 變成被它控制了 都是做它的
And then break down the cell
然後呢 再把這個細胞分解掉
Spread the power of this virus out
把這個病毒的圍力呢 擴散出去
to infect more cells, so we'll produce
再去感染更多的細胞 所以我們呢就會生產
When it is about to leave, this N I just mentioned
當它要離開的時候呢 這個N我剛剛講過
It is a hydrolase of lyrenic acid
它是一個透益酸的水解酶
It will cut the cell above it and cut it off
它就會把細胞上面的 就會把它切掉
Otherwise it won't get out it will stick to this
不然的話它跑不出去 它會黏在這個上面
This production of our cell breakdown
我們細胞破掉的這個產生
it's glued on so it won't get infected
它被黏在上面它就不會去感染
So this N, so H and N are related to torenic acid
所以這個N 所以H跟N都跟透益酸有關
One, H is the rapid number of torenic acid
一個呢 H就是透益酸的凌急數
It can stick to it. N is the hydrolase of the acid
它可以跟它黏 N就是透益酸的水解酶
We all know that we know about the gag flu
大家都知道 我們知道這個克流感
People who have taken the flu have heard that it is very effective
克流感吃過的人聽說非常有效
In fact, if you eat it on the real machine, your cold will heal very quickly.
事實上實機吃的話呢 感冒好得非常快
Why
為什麼
But what is the flu?
但是克流感又是什麼呢?
What about the flu?
克流感呢
it is
它是
What about the flu? It's a cold virus.
克流感呢它是感冒病毒
This N is an enzyme
這個N它是一個酵素嘛
This N is an enzyme that hydrolyzes stripping acid
這個N它是水解脫衣酸的酵素
its inhibitor
它的抑制劑
It suppresses the function of this N
它把這個N的功能把它抑制掉
Reduce the ability of the virus to spread
讓病毒擴散的能力減低
It can be seen that the gram flu is
可以看到克流感是
Rosu medicine
Rosu藥腸
it is eaten
它是用吃的
what about the other one
另外一個呢
What about another medicine?
另外一種藥呢是
Gran vegetarian sausage
Gran素藥腸
it is sprayed
它是用噴的
It's because the medicine is like this
是因為呢藥是這樣子藥
If your medicine is too watery
你如果藥清水性太強
eat it
吃下去
It didn't take long to get rid of it
沒有多久就排掉了
you eat
你吃
B vitamins are water soluble
維他命B就是水溶性的
you eat for about a few hours
你吃大概幾個小時
It's yellow when you pee
你去小便的話就黃色的
This is clear water
這是清水性
So stay longer
所以要再身體留久一點
You need to be more watery
你就要比較聚水性的
passenger flu
客流感
This whole structure is relatively water-accumulating
這整個結構它是比較聚水
it can be eaten
它可以用吃的
This water is relatively strong
這個清水性比較大
it is sprayed
它就是用噴的
let's see
我們來看看
If there is guest flu
如果有客流感在的時候
it puts N
它把N
this N
這個N
when its function is inhibited
它的功能抑制掉的時候
if you don't have guest flu
如果你沒有客流感的時候
you can see
你可以看到
This is a little bit dark
這個一點一點黑黑的
It's a little dark
這一點一點黑黑的
cold virus
就是感冒病毒
it's in this cell
它在這個細胞裡面
keep growing
一直滋長滋長
Then what
然後呢
grow to the end
滋長到最後
burst this cell
把這個細胞撐破
And then put it in the particles of this cold virus
然後把它的這個感冒病毒的顆粒
Micro force spreads out
微力往外擴散
to infect more cells
再去感染更多的細胞
at this time
這個時候
if you have gram flu
如果你有克流感
it can't put
它沒辦法把
When the stripping acid is cut completely
脫衣酸切得很完全的時候
you can see
你可以看到
you see a lot
你看很多的
cold granules
感冒顆粒
cold particles are
感冒顆粒就被
caught in these cell membranes
就被抓在這些細胞膜
broken cell membrane
殘破的細胞膜的上面
you can see
你可以看到
With the flu and without the flu
有克流感跟沒有克流感
this is no gram flu
這是沒有克流感
its difference
它的差別
they mean
他們是說
if you have the flu
如果有克流感的時候
the gram flu you eat
你吃的克流感
The spread rate of this cold
這個感冒的擴散率
will be halved
會減半
or at least 40% off
或至少減掉40%
At this moment
這時候
it goes infected
它去感染
capacity of other cells
別的細胞的能力
will be greatly reduced
就會大為下降
good
好
I will re-enter now
我現在再進入
another subject
另外一個課題
is nosocomial infection
是院內感染
What about nosocomial infection? You see the hospital.
院內感染呢 你看醫院
The hospital is disinfected every day
醫院每天消毒
Then, what about the patients? Patients from all over the place went in again with bacteria.
然後呢 病人呢 又四處的病人帶著菌又進去
Disinfect again
又消毒
So the sick hospital is a nursery
所以病醫院呢 是一個應育
In a place where superbugs are grown
在培養超級細菌的一個地方
What are superbugs?
什麼是超級細菌呢
is that it is a multi-drug resistant
就是它是一個多重抗藥性的
multidrug resistant bacteria
多重抗藥性的細菌
It's when your antibiotics are initially effective
就是你的抗生素用得最初有效
The more you use it, the less effective the more you use it
越用越沒效 越用越
So nosocomial infection is a very scary
所以院內感染是一個非常可怕的
It's like talking about Staphylococcus aureus bacteria, Lilong infection bacteria
就像說金黃色葡萄菊菌啊 立龍感菌啊
Or S. pneumoniae, a bunch of bacteria.
或者肺炎鏈菊菌啊 一堆菌
those
那這些
Some bacteria are very poisonous and some bacteria are actually not very poisonous
有些菌是很毒 有些菌事實上沒有很毒
But what about older people?
那但是呢 年長的人呢
or people with chronic diseases like diabetes
或者有慢性病像糖尿病的人
people with weak immunity
能獲得免疫力比較差的人
Once he got to the hospital it was easy
他一到醫院就很容易
This is the high risk group
這就高危險群
These superbugs or multi-drug resistant bacteria
這些超級細菌或者多同抗藥細菌
it's easy to find him
就很容易去找到他
it will be like this
就會這樣
to the hospital
到醫院
The hospital is not a place of intersection
醫院不是一個交集的地方
don't go
千萬不要去
if you are not sick
如果你沒有病的話
if you must go
如果你一定要去
when you come out
那你出來的時候
be sure to wash your hands
一定要洗手
Washing hands is one of the best defenses
洗手是一個防禦最好的
Or you wear a mask and wash your hands
或者你戴口罩洗手
that's all the best
那都是最好的
nosocomial infection
那院內感染
people have predictions
人家就有預測
like good
像好
this
這個
The economist two years ago said
那兩年前的經濟學人就把說
These multi-drug resistant things
這些多同抗藥菌的事情
This creates a medical crisis for humanity
這會產生人類的醫療危機
use it as a cover
把它當成封面
He said
他說
this
這個
multidrug resistant bacteria
這些多同抗藥菌細菌
you to the end
你到最後
No
沒有
can't find
已經找不到
kill him
抗生處去殺他
He not only reports
他不只他報導啦
like the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention has also reported
像美國的疾病管制局也有報告
For these multi-drug resistant
對這些多同抗藥訊的
he also has a report
他也有報告
The weekly newsletter of the American Chemical Society
美國化學會的每一週的通訊
He also reported this as a cover
他也有把這個當成一個封面在報導
both years ago
都是好幾年前就
people are aware of the crisis
人家就意識到這個危機
if an elderly person goes to the hospital
如果年老的人去住院
What if you are
如果你是
Who are you
你是
The cancer patient is better or your other patients are better
癌症病患好了或者你其他的病患好
to the end
到最後
In fact, many, probably more than half of the people
事實上很多大概有一半以上的人
all died of sepsis
都是死於敗血
nosocomial infection
就是院內感染
septicemia
敗血
What is septicemia
敗血是什麼
Septicemia is when bacteria get into your blood
敗血就是細菌跑到你的學藝裡面
in charge
執掌
and make you inflamed blood
然後讓你發炎血液
blood inflammation
血液發炎
Then what
然後呢
will be yours
就會 你的
Because your immune system is weak, you will be infected
因為你的免疫力弱嘛 就會被感染
blood to
血液到
What about invading bacteria? Will it cause inflammation?
侵入的細菌呢 就會引起發炎嘛
to take charge so that in the end it is
來執掌 所以到最後都是
Light exhaustion, or something, just die
氣光衰竭啊 或什麼 就這樣死掉
This is a very serious medical issue
這個是一個非常嚴重的 在醫療啊 這方面
What causes sepsis is
那引起敗血的就是
There are some bacteria, some bacteria
細菌有一些 有部分的細菌呢
polysaccharide
它是有止多糖
This is liver sepsis. In fact, it is also related to
這個是肝 敗血事實上也跟
sugar related
糖有關的
So how do we solve the problem of nosocomial infection?
那如何 我們要如何解決院內感染的問題呢
I think we can find new antibiotics
我想 我們可以找新的抗生素
Dean Weng recently had a paper
翁院長最近有一篇論文
well done if you are in
做成很好 你如果在
The cover of our campus Zhongyuan Hospital
我們院區 中原院的封面
he saw
他就有看到
he develops new
他發展新的
new antibiotics
新的抗生素
antibiotic
抗生素的
you use
你一用
He'll be resistant right away
他馬上就有抗藥性出來
Therefore, many pharmaceutical companies are not willing to develop
所以很多藥廠是不太願意發展
Because his cycle is too fast
因為他的週期太快
other profits
他利潤
development is difficult
發展是很困難
but
但是
Xu Jun is smarter than you
虛俊比你還聰明
Hsu Jun wants to be a few generations later
虛俊他要幾個世代之後
He will be resistant to your antibiotics, and he will come out.
他就抗你的抗生素的種就就出來
another one?
另外一種呢
You need to bring your own preventive vaccines
你要自備預防型的疫苗
otherwise you will
不然的話你就
prevention
預防
I think
我覺得
Prevention of residual treatment
預防剩餘治療
So I am more inclined to make vaccines
所以我比較偏向於做疫苗
what is the vaccine for
這個疫苗要什麼
sugar required
要糖質
It's the superficial appearance
就是虛俊表面的
polysaccharide
多糖
used as an antigen
拿來當抗原
make a vaccine
做成疫苗
you
你們
Glucose antibiotics are now on the market
現在市面上有著糖質抗
As for vaccines, the most famous one is that we don’t care about others.
疫苗呢 最出名的就是 我們其他不要看好了
Let's take a look at the pneumococcal vaccine.
我們來看呢 這個肺炎鏈球鏡疫苗
Was Taipei City in October or December last year?
台北市在去年10月還是12月
That is, if you are 65 years old, you can get the pneumococcal vaccine, right?
就是你年紀上65歲 你就可以去打肺炎鏈球鏡疫苗對不對
I used to be 75 years old, all of Taiwan
以前是75歲 是全台灣的
like last year 2001
好像去年2001年
this taipei city
這台北市
From October to December, as long as there are four people over 65 years old in Taipei
10月到12月 只要是台北四名65歲以上
You can subsidize a shot of 23 pneumococcal vaccines
就可以補助打一針23架的肺炎鏈球鏡疫苗
There are 23, there are 13, what is the difference?
有23架 有13架到底差在哪裡啊
Right? Pneumonia streptoscopic
對不對 肺炎鏈球鏡
I should go for a phone call, if I accidentally get hospitalized at my age
我應該要去打 像我這種年紀如果不小心住院的時候
If I get pneumonia streptoscopic
我感染到肺炎鏈球鏡的話
Then maybe I'm miserable too
那可能我也很慘
What is it? It says 23 are Streptococcus pneumoniae polysaccharide vaccines
什麼是 它說23家是肺炎鏈球菌多糖體疫苗
Those 13 are Streptococcus pneumoniae vaccines
那13家是肺炎鏈球菌疫苗
What is the full name Conjugated pneumococcal vaccine
全名是什麼 結合型肺炎鏈球菌疫苗
If I tell you like this, will you hear me?
如果這樣跟你講 你會 聽到沒有
ok then let me explain why
好 那我幫你解釋 為什麼
What is what is a polysaccharide vaccine
什麼是 什麼是多糖疫苗
What is a conjugate vaccine
什麼是結合型的疫苗
I explain to you
我解釋給你們聽
As I just said, bacteria have a layer of polysaccharides on their surface
我剛剛講過 細菌的表面有一層多糖
If we do our research
我們如果 我們在做研究的時候
This polysaccharide will be separated and purified
就會把這個多糖分離出來 純化出來
superficial without damaging cells
表面的 沒有破壞細胞
don't break the cells
不把細胞打破
It is the polysaccharide on the surface that purifies it
就是表面的這個多糖把它純化出來
This is the polysaccharide on the surface I am now
這個就是表面的多糖 我現在
Okay, what about the 23rd one? The purified polysaccharides are just shot directly.
好 23家那個呢 就這純化出來的多糖直接就打
hit you directly
就直接就打在你的身上
Of course they must have done some evaluation.
當然他們一定有做一些評估啊
Doing that will cause a funeral, it’s not as simple as what I said
做那個要要喪事 沒有那麼我講的這麼簡單
What are the 13 companies?
那13家的是什麼呢
13 is the one who wants the polysaccharide
13家呢是他要把這個多糖
connect him to this carrier
把他接在這個載體
This carrier is protein
這個載體是蛋白哦
attached to this carrier
接在這個載體
This polysaccharide should be connected to this sugar
這個多糖呢要把它接在這個糖
Anyway, this sugar is an antigen
再怎麼樣這個糖呢就是一個抗原
No matter if you use polysaccharide to make it or you connect it to a protein carrier to make it
不管你是用多糖去打或者你把它接在一個蛋白的載體上面去打
your major antigen
你的主要的抗原
These are the antigens that produce antibodies
要產生抗體的就是這一些抗原就是這一些
sugar
糖
You only need to connect to this protein
你只要有接在你只要有接在這個蛋白上面
They are called conjugate vaccines
他們就叫結合疫苗
what's the difference between these two
那這兩個有什麼不一樣
sorry it's complicated
對不起 這很複雜
but i simplified it
但是我把它簡單化
If you are a multiple
如果你是一個多堂
when the vaccine
當疫苗的時候
Dodo when the vaccine
多堂當疫苗的時候
you may
你有可能
your efficiency is short
你的效率很短
The most important thing for us to vaccinate is to
我們打疫苗最主要的是要
what do we want most
我們最主要的要什麼
have a memory
要有記憶
have immune memory
要有免疫的記憶
That is to say, I have been separated by two years
就是說我隔了兩年
three years later
三年之後呢
if the same
如果同樣的
antigen comes in
抗原進來
will replace my immune memory
會換起我的免疫的記憶
Because many of us are vaccinated
因為很多我們打了疫苗
not every few years
隔幾年就沒有
Same goes for the cold vaccine
感冒疫苗也一樣
After you hit it, you have to last for a long time
打了之後你要維持久
Influenza vaccine every year
感冒疫苗每年都要打
If you are vaccinated with sugar
你如果是打糖質的疫苗的話
If you take sugar vaccine
你如果打糖質疫苗
your effect
你效果
is relatively short
是比較短暫的
because it has less immune memory
因為它比較沒有免疫的記憶
Why compare memory without immunity? Because
為什麼比較沒有免疫的記憶?因為
The antibodies it produces do not
它產生的抗體沒有
Let's say that the cells that produce antibodies are called B cells.
我們說產生抗體的細胞之後叫做B細胞好了
Antibody-producing cells are not activated by T cells
產生抗體的細胞沒有經過T細胞的活化
but if you
但是你如果
yes
是
is useful that
是有用那個
combined vaccine words
結合疫苗的話
It has a longer memory
它記憶力會比較長
the effect will be longer
效果會比較長
That's because, as long as you connect it to the egg white
那因為呢你只要有接在蛋白上面
it will
它就會
Destimulate T cells from V cells
從V細胞去刺激T細胞
T cells come back to activate
T細胞再回來活化
V cells give it memory
V細胞讓它有記憶
I'm not an immunologist myself
我自己本身也不是免疫學家
so i can't make this clear
所以我沒辦法把這個講清楚
But it's the difference
但是它的差別就在這裡
even
甚至呢
If you directly use this polysaccharide
如果直接用打這個多糖的時候
Not good for children under two years old
小孩子兩歲以下效果不好
or older
或者年紀比較大
Sometimes the effect is not good
效果有的時候也不好
So they have to work hard
所以他們呢就要努力
make it into a conjugate vaccine
把它做成結合型的疫苗
This is part of my research
這個呢是我做研究的一部分
you can see
你可以看到
look at this bacteria
你看這個細菌
This is the bacteria on the cultivated rice
這個就是細菌在培養米上面
One by one for many years
一顆一顆多年
why is it so sticky
這些為什麼它會這麼黏
because of its shell
就是因為它的外殼
The outer shell of this bacterium has a strong sugar
這個細菌的外殼有一層很強的糖
very thick sugar
很厚的糖
what about this
那這個呢
we're going to separate it
我們就要把它分離出來
then made
然後做成
make that antidote vaccine
做成那個解藥性疫苗
Why is the shell of the bacteria so thick with sugar?
那細菌的外殼為什麼要有這麼厚的糖
Once it enters our body
它一旦進到我們人體的話
it has that layer of protection
它有那一層保護
It won't be swallowed by our immune cells
它不會被我們的免疫細胞吞掉的
And what about the layer of sugar?
而且呢 它這一層糖呢
will poison us again
又會毒害我們
Protecting it can poison us
保護它又可以對我們造成毒害
ok then i
好 那我
about the same time
時間也差不多
i speak faster now
我現在講快一點
our healthy food
我們這健康食品嘛
The third and last part I will talk about healthy food
第三 第最後一個部分我就講健康食品
Dragon Boat Festival is coming
端午節快到了
Everyone will eat zongzi
大家會去吃粽子
but everyone knows
但是大家都知道
Don't eat too much rice dumplings
吃粽子不要吃多
Because zongzi is difficult to digest
因為粽子比較難消化
Why Zongzi Are Difficult To Digest
為什麼粽子比較難消化
We have to look at its structure
我們要從它的結構來看
can you see
你可以看到呢
if we are
我們如果是
If glutinous rice is used, it will have a lot of nourishment
糯米的話,它就會有很多滋煉
It nourishes a lot, this is glutinous rice
它滋煉上很多,這個就是糯米
This place that is a little bit red is
一點一點紅紅的這個地方就是
is the non-reducing end, that is, the enzyme
就是非還原端,也就是酵素
Enzymes can decompose, enzymes can decompose
酵素可以分解,酵素可以分解的
So it has many places to decompose and can decompose at the same time
所以它有很多地方可以分解,可以同時分解
But if you have less nourishment, probably you only have one or two
但是你如果呢,滋煉比較少,大概你只有一條或兩條
So in general, it works very quickly at the beginning
所以一般的,它一剛開始可以作用很快
So glutinous rice is the first, it has a high glycemic index
所以糯米第一個,它升糖指數很快
Because it works very quickly at the beginning, your glycemic index is very fast
因為它剛開始作用很快,你升糖指數就很快
But, when its enzymes work until
但是呢,當它酵素一直作用到
When reaching this branch point, close to this branch
到這個分支點的時候,接近這個分支
At the branch point, the enzyme will stop
分支點的時候,那個酵素就會停下來
Because it can't work anymore, it needs to be replaced with another set
因為它沒辦法再作用,它要再換另外一套的
Enzymes can continue to do
酵素才能夠再繼續做
At this moment
這時候
it will, because you can't
它就會,因為你沒辦法在分之前就
We humans can't absorb it
就我們人不能吸收啊
Therefore, it cannot be decomposed
所以造成,它也分解不下
It uses another enzyme to break down
它又用另外一個酵素來分解
So digestion slows down
所以一下消化就變慢
Slow down and you will bloat
變慢你就會脹啊
Why does it swell?
為什麼會脹?
Because Syria will use
因為敘敘會來利用
Sometimes talk, because you can't digest
有的時候敘敘,因為你消化就不
Digestion is fast at first, but when it arrives
剛開始消化很快,但是到了
Indigestion and indigestion later
後面又消化又不良
So this glutinous rice you have to see
所以這個糯米你要去看
its branches, its branches
它的分支,它的分支
The so-called look at this side, this side is all
所謂你看這邊是,這邊都是
Alpha one four connection
阿法一四連接嘛
The branch is to become alpha-16 to connect
分支就是變成阿法一六來連接
it has many branches
它很多分支
Many branches will decompose quickly
很多分支前面會分解得快
Decomposes slowly
後面分解得慢
Caused by high glycemic index
造成前面生糖指數高
I'll let you back
後面又讓你呢
Poor digestion
消化不好
Because it is slow, so glutinous rice
因為慢,所以糯米
Its indigestibility depends on the structure of its starch
它的難消化要從它的澱粉的結構去看
it will be clear
就會很清楚
Some people have diarrhea after drinking milk
有的人呢 有些人喝牛奶也會拉肚子
What about milk diarrhea?
牛奶拉肚子呢 為什麼
Because it's in the milk
因為呢 牛奶裡面的
Mostly lactose, this lactose is a disaccharide
大部分是乳糖 這個乳糖是雙糖
disaccharide
雙糖
We can't directly absorb and utilize this disaccharide
我們不能直接吸收利用 我們要把這個雙糖
This lactose is broken down into
這個乳糖呢 分解成
Galactose
半乳糖跟
with this glucose
跟這個葡萄糖
have a valid number called lactose hydrolase
要有一個效數 叫做乳糖水解酶
You break it down into a galactose heel
你把它分解 變成一個半乳糖跟
That glucose we can use the simple sugar we can use
那葡萄糖 我們就可以單糖 我們就可以利用
But unfortunately, some people
但是很可惜 就是有一些人
no way
沒辦法
or secreted this
或分泌的這個
lactose hydrolase
乳糖水解酶
very few
非常少
Or, there is no way to decompose it at this time
或者呢 沒辦法分解 這時候
What about the bacteria hiding inside?
藏到裡面的細菌呢
will come to use
就會來利用
You don't need it, we often go there, there are bacteria in it
你不用嘛 我們常到裡面本來就有細菌嘛
just take advantage
就來利用
The result is often until the bacteria you have been using have been growing a lot
結果常到細菌你一直利用 一直長長很多
Then you have diarrhea or gas or something.
那你就拉肚子啦 或者脹氣啊 或者什麼
that's why you milk
這就為什麼 你牛奶
Drinking milk will stretch your stomach and make you gas
喝牛奶 會拉住肚子 會脹氣
In fact, it has something to do with sugar, your breakdown of sugar.
事實上跟糖也有關係 跟你對糖的分解
It does matter, sometimes pigs do too.
是有關係的 有時候豬也會啊
If a pig feeds him this
豬如果給他吃的這個
this in beans
豆子裡面這個
its sugary
它的糖的
material
資料
Pigs can't digest well
豬沒辦法消化得很好
What about the pigs, the bacteria in the sugar will grow
豬呢 裡面的糖到的細菌就會長起來
will be like us
也會跟我們一樣
And what about vitamin C, as we all know
那還有呢 大家都知道像維他命C
I eat one almost every day
我幾乎每天都吃一顆啦
Then we can't synthesize it, we humans can't synthesize it
那我們是沒辦法合成 我們人是沒辦法合成
Most animals can synthesize
大部分的動物都可以合成
People I know with this Catholic agency
我所知道的人跟這個天主署
Fighting again today
今天又拼了
These two are unable to synthesize vitamin C
這兩種是沒辦法合成維他命C
Vitamin C in industry
維他命C在工業上面呢
it comes directly from glucose
它就直接從葡萄糖來
in other plants or animals
在其他的植物或是積綽動物
They can also be directly converted into vitamin C from glucose
他們也是從葡萄糖直接就可以變成維他命C
Cut down on vitamin C
切少維他命C
your gold
你的金
Your gold strength must not be strong enough
你的金強韌度一定不夠
This is industrial glucose
這個是工業葡萄糖
Then after two steps it can
然後經過兩步它就可以
Vitamin C can be produced
就可以把維他命C給生產出來
Let's talk about sugar
那下面講代糖
sugar substitute
代糖有一種代糖
was discovered in England in 1976
是在1976年在英國發現
In the United States it was 1998
在美國是1998年的時候
approved
核准
that is, its useful life
也就是它的使用的年限
perhaps
大概
20 years
20多年
Sugar gold is in 18 years
糖金是在18幾年
only century
只有世紀就有了
These discoveries of sugar substitutes were made by me by accident.
這些代糖的發現都是無意間讓我發現的
Then this sugar substitute is called Splendor
那這個代糖它的商品名叫Splendor
Splendor it's made from this sugar
Splendor它是從這糖變過來的
The part of the OH with a red dot is all replaced by this green
打紅點的這個OH的這個部分全部都被這個綠取代
Its sweetness is about 600 times that of sugar
它這個甜度大概是這糖600倍
So, but its advantage is that it is not metabolized in the digestive system
所以呢但是它的好處是在在消化系統是不被代謝
can be almost eliminated from the body
可以幾乎都會排除體外
That is to say, if you don’t know if anyone can substitute sugar for this R48 sweetener
也就是說你如果不知道有沒有人代糖吃這個R48甜
R48 sweetness is calculated by two calculations
R48甜是按計算兩個按計算做起來
R48 is sweet and this is sweeter than R48 because it is calculated
R48甜跟這個比R48甜因為它的按計算
If there are amino acids, one of the 20,000 people will have some problems with the metabolism of amino acids
如果有對胺基酸,這兩萬個人會有一個對胺基酸的代謝會有一些問題
it produces disease
它就會產生疾病
Then Aspartia is about 220 times the same as this set
那阿斯巴田大概是220倍跟這套
Aspartia also has a bad place, that is
阿斯巴田也有一個不好的地方就是
Once it's baked, it's about as sweet as
它如果一烘烤的話,它甜度大概會像是
If it's put in soda, it will also slowly descend
它如果放在汽水裡面的話,它也會慢慢下降
Because soda, if you add carbon dioxide to soda, there will be no carbonation
因為汽水,你如果把二氧化碳加到汽水裡面就沒有碳酸
What is the Ph value of carbonated soda?
碳酸汽水是讓它的Ph值是多少?
4, or lower, how much carbonic acid?
4,還是更低,碳酸看多少?
Anyway, it won't be neutral, it should be acidic
反正不會是中性的就是應該是偏酸
At this time, it is possible for Aspartia to
這時候阿斯巴田就有可能
Aspartame may lose its sweetness slowly
阿斯巴田有可能它的甜度就會慢慢消失
but this thing it won't
但是這個東西它不會
Its trade name is Sprander
它的商品名叫Sprander
that real name is
那真正的名字叫
Sucrose
Sucrose
Frankly, I ate this
坦白講我吃這個啦
because it's cheap a kilo
因為這個很便宜 一公斤
Seven or eight thousand Taiwan dollars, made in Canada
七八千塊台幣 加拿大做的
then you can too
那你也可以 我在
where am i here
我在什麼地方 我在這個
Where
什麼地方
foreign
國外的
I'm abroad this
我在國外的這個
Summerway saw that they added this
Summerway 有看到他們有加這個
Summerway
Summerway
add this
有加這個
That
那
good i think
好 我想
Everyone should be familiar with bird's nest
對燕窩來講 大家應該不陌生
Because we Orientals, especially Chinese
因為我們東方人 尤其是中國人
think bird's nest is a
認為燕窩是一個
It's a good nourishment, isn't it?
很好的一個滋養品嘛 對不對
Bird's nest is actually good or bad
燕窩事實上它的好壞
Decide on two Decide whether it's good or bad There are two
決定兩個 決定它的好壞有兩個
One is protein and the other is sugar
一個是蛋白 一個就是糖
Bird's nest is believed to contain
燕窩是認為含有
sugar
糖
High amount of dehydrating acid
高量的脫液酸
His good or bad dehydrating acid if the content is high
他的好壞 脫液酸如果含量高
they think it's good
他們就認為是好
I'm sorry because I don't know
對不起 因為我不知道
what if i ate it
如果真正吃了呢
Does it have nutritional or health benefits?
他到底有沒有營養或保健的功效
I do not know about this
這個我不知道
I'm going to ask that nutritionist
這要去問那個營養師
okay i say good things
好不好 我講說很好的話
That leaf environmentalist is here to scold me
那葉環保人是為了來罵我
I'm sorry because I really don't know
對不起 因為我真的不知道
Is it good or bad to eat bird's nest?
吃燕窩到底好或不好
Then bring it down
那帶下來呢
This is my real experiment
這個是我真正的實驗
I did the last two years
我做了 最近兩年做的
That is to say, everyone will say
也就是大家都會說
edible mushroom polysaccharide
食用菇類 多醣體
I really polysaccharides in my experiment
我在我的實驗裡面真的多醣體
It's mushrooms
就是菇類
two kinds of mushrooms
兩種菇
One is dirty beef juice
一個是牛髒汁
one is black fungus
一個是黑木耳
he really
他真的呢
we confirm
我們證實
He can really enhance people's immunity
他真的是可以增強人的免疫力
It activates giant cells
它可以活化巨式細胞
These giant cells are our immune cells
這巨式細胞就是我們的免疫細胞
It can increase the bactericidal phagocytosis of giant cells
它可以增加巨式細胞的殺菌吞噬的能力
can also increase the strength of a person who inhales endotoxins
也可以增強如果吸進內毒素的人受力
If we say that when we get infected in the hospital
如果說我們在院內感染的時候
If we usually eat more of these mushrooms
我們平常有多吃這些菇類的話
It is possible to suffer from the septicemia just now
就有可能受到的這個內就剛剛的這個敗血
It will be lessened, maybe
就會減輕一點 也說不定
this of course it is we are
這個當然它是我們是
The polysaccharide structure of this beef dirty juice
把這個牛髒汁的多醣結構
analyze it and see how it looks
把它分析完 然後再看看它是怎麼樣
This part of the reaction is doing Yilan University
這一部分的反應就是在做宜蘭大學
Professor Hua helped us do it
這個花教授幫忙我們做的
Well, some people also say that this is the starting value of chitin
好 也有人說這個起丁值甲殼素
These are polysaccharides
這些都是多糖
Then sometimes this can be used in agriculture
那有的時候這個可以用到農業嘛
Can enhance plant health or
可以增強植物的健康啊或者
Resistance
抵抗力啊
Some people also say that you eat alphanuclides
也有人說你吃甲核素呢
Can lose weight and lower cholesterol
可以減肥啊可以降低膽固醇
because
因為
There are some alphanuclides it is put this
有一些甲核素呢它是把這個
by
以
to suck
以吸
After this cut it off
這個把它切掉之後
it is belt
它是帶
It is also positively charged
它也是帶正電的
can put some
可以呢把一些
What about charged fatty acids?
帶復電的脂肪酸呢
take it
把它
Adsorb and then
吸附然後
take it out of the body
把它帶帶出體外
Some people say it can lose weight
有人說可以減肥啊這個
I don't know
這我不知道
But there are many healthy foods
但是呢健康食品很多
squeeze nails
都是用擠釘子
Squeeze the nail is the top
擠釘子是上面
Then a nuclide
然後甲核素
just leave it at this
就就把它這個
this
這個
this removes it
這個把它去掉
just let it electrify
就讓它帶電
What about this one? I encourage you a little.
那這個呢像我微鼓勵
this is the same
這個也是一樣
This micro-encouragement is the same
這微鼓勵呢也是一樣都是
Grape Chang'an
葡萄長安
It is mainly a cartilage mechanism
它最主要它是一個軟骨機質的
like our joints
像我們的關節
Osteoarthritis as we age
我們年紀大的人會有退化性關節炎
Osteoarthritis is primarily
退化性關節炎最主要就是
Why do our joints have cartilage?
我們關節為什麼要有軟骨
because it is mainly cartilage-forming
因為它主要是形成軟骨的
Cartilage absorbs a lot of water
軟骨就是吸食很多水分
increase the awareness of this joint
增加這個關節的認華
So Glucose
所以葡萄糖安
It can provide you with this recognition
它可以提供你這個認華
Can also do this hyaluronic acid is also a glucose
也可以做這個波尿酸也是一個葡萄糖
It can also be a type of hyaluronic acid
也可以是波尿酸的一種
like hyaluronic acid
像波尿酸
it's more useful
它用途更大了
Whether it is cosmetic moisturizing
這個不管是化妝品保濕
The current ones can be mass-produced with follow-up
那目前的都是用續進的可以大量生產
what was the earliest
最早是什麼
Take it out from the organ, the attacking organ
從機關 攻擊的機關裡面抽出來
What is the use of
用途是什麼
If you go to some places like Hong Kong, there is Saima
你如果到有些地方像香港有塞馬
Saima's horse
塞馬的馬啊
it joint this this
它關節這個這個
Saima joints are treated with cloth uric acid
塞馬關節都打這個布尿酸的
I don't know if the real Saima is playing in the early days or not
真正塞馬早期現在有沒有打我不知道
I used to watch when I was a kid and I couldn't understand
以前我小時候就看我看不懂
But that's all he uses
不過這個就是他任何用的
Well, I think this molecule has a lot of cousins.
好我想這個還有很多堂子的分子
In fact, it's related to both cancer and the immune system.
事實上是跟癌症來免疫系統都有關
In fact
事實上呢
In front of Vice President Liu, I'm playing tricks
我在劉副院長面前是班門弄斧
In fact, er, Vice President Liu is also an expert of Tangzi.
這個事實上呃劉副院長也是堂子的專家
Especially in this galactose
尤其他在這個半乳糖
Galactose
半乳糖的
Galactose Lingjisu 3
半乳糖凌吉素3
It's our Vice President Liu
是我們劉副院長
found
發現的
Is it related to cancer?
跟癌症先方有關嘛
If you are on this side
那如果你們要是這一方面的話
of course to ask
當然要去請教
Vice President Liu, I, I, really
劉副院長我我真的
So when I talk about this, I probably want to say something
所以我講到這邊我大概話上句
But at the end I want to introduce Tangzi Science Education Foundation to you
但是我到最後要跟大家介紹唐子科學教育基金會
Minister Liu just said that the police mourned the professor and his wife
剛剛那個劉部長講過警喪教授他們夫婦
to Taiwan in 1996
在1996年到台灣
Because at that time the University of Tokyo was a national university in Japan
因為那時候東京大學日本的國立大學
It is about 60 years old and must retire
大概就是60歲一定要退休
So he in 1994
所以他在1994年
Why does he have so much affection for Taiwan?
為什麼他對台灣有這麼大的感情呢
because he is born
因為他就是完生
he was born in taiwan
他是在台灣出生
Then he didn't return to Japan until he was 11 or 12 years old
然後一直到他11、12歲的時候才回日本
So he returned to Japan in 1945 or 1946
所以他1945還是1946回日本
So he is willing to come to Taiwan
所以他願意到台灣來
And in Taiwan
而且在台灣呢
and his wife's salary are all built
跟他太太的薪水都建出來
Establish the Tangzi Foundation
成立這個唐子基金會
At that time, of course, Dean Li was established in 2002
當時呢當然李院長那是2002年成立的
Dean Li also went to raise funds
李院長也去募款
There are several like Uniform Yimei
有好幾個像統一 義美
and gold car
還有金車
And Yong Fengyu's family
還有勇豐宇 四家
Under the call of Dean Li
在李院長的號召之下
Also set up a foundation
也兼了全成立了基金會
But in 2003
但是2003年的時候
Former Dean Weng returned to Taiwan
翁前院長就回到台灣
Foundation Center
主持了基金體中心
His power is much greater than the foundation
他的力量要比基金會大很多
Over the past 10 years, our foundation
我們這個基金會在過去的10年
didn't play very well
沒有很大發揮
Because Dean Weng has taken the lead in
因為翁院長已經帶頭在
make a lot of pushes in this direction
做很多這一方面的推動
In the future, I hope that everyone
日後我是希望大家
Learn about our foundation
對我們基金會能夠了解
In fact our slogan is
事實上我們的口號就是
Kangzhi Technology Anti-disease and anti-aging
康直科技 抗病防老
This is our logo
這個是我們的Logo
ok thank you all
好 謝謝大家
Thanks
謝謝
Well, thanks to Dr. Wu Zhixiong for being very informative
好,感謝吳志雄博士非常內容豐富
and a very careful speech
而且講得非常仔細的一個演講
So now open up some of that questioning
那麼現在開放一些那個發問
I also encourage you to ask
我也鼓勵大家發問
So if we ask
所以我們如果發問的話
would give a very nice one
都會給一個非常漂亮的一個
Is it a cup type cup electricity?
就是杯式杯電嘛
ok over here
好,那這邊
Why is the non-reducing side crowded out of here
為什麼非還原端要擠在這裡外面
can say it again
可以再講一次
This is a basic structure of Tang Zi
這是唐子的一個基本的一個結構嘛
he must
他一定
almost always use one to pick up
幾乎一定用一去接
he can pick up at six
他可以接在六
can be picked up in four
可以接在四
can be connected in three
可以接在三
can be connected in two
可以接在二
As long as there is OH, he can pick it up
只要有OH的地方他都可以接
Tropical acid exception
托一酸例外
Tropical acid is connected with two
托一酸是用二去接
But his structure is
但是他結構就是
just the same
就是一樣
that is
就是
Take it like this, after you take it
這樣接,你接完之後
The non-reducing end must be the outermost
非還原端一定是在最外面
because he was connected
因為他接在
He combines with fat or with
他跟脂肪結合或者跟
protein binding is to use his
蛋白結合是用他的
restore terminal
還原端去接
That one, didn’t you mention H and N just now?
那那個啊,就是剛剛不是有講到H跟N嗎
Isn't that N used to cut that H?
那個N不是用來切那個H的嗎
N is cutting acid
N是在切脫一酸的
cut acid
切脫一酸
Because it is deacidified, hydrolyzed
因為他是脫一酸,水解沒
N
N
So if you see H1N1
所以你如果看到H1N1
this is him
這個就是他在
He has many categories, like H generally has 16 categories
他有很多類,像H一般是有16類
N has 9 categories
N有9類
this is normal
這是一般的
Then how to divide it, yes
那這怎麼分呢,是
it's this virus that got to us
是這個病毒到我們
Antibodies produced by the body
人體產生的這些抗體
Sometimes these antibodies are used to classify
有時候用這些抗體去分類
The N will only work after he has to leave
他是一定要離開之後那個N才會作用
or before infection he will
還是在感染之前他就會
this is a good question
這個是一個好問題
Its virus is a very good distribution of H and N
它這個病毒就是H跟N分配的很好
H is about 3 to 4 times N
H大概是N的大概3到4倍
About 3 to 4 times outside
在外外大概3到4倍
If I hadn't been very careful just now
如果我剛剛沒有很仔細講
I said its amount is the amount on the surface of the virus
我說它的量在病毒的表面的量
H will be more than N
H會比N多
about 3 to 4 times more
大概多到3到4倍
So when it is picked up, N must play first
所以它在接的時候就N要先發揮
I said N it's going to find dehydrating acid
我說N它要去找脫液酸
The dehydrating acid must be found at the outermost end
脫液酸一定是在最外端去找
then this is the first step
然後這是第一步
It is the first step to enter the cell
它要進到細胞的第一步
I think I still want to ask about vaccines.
我覺得想還想問就是剛剛有講到疫苗
What does 13 plus 23 plus mean?
就是有什麼13加23加那是什麼意思
That is to say, if you go to see dried mushrooms in Tai Tam
就是說你如果去看大潭幹菌
I use Tai Tam dried fungus and everyone will know better
我用大潭幹菌大家會比較了解
a bacteria
一種序菌
its
它的
Sugar out there is ever-changing
外面的糖千變萬化
ever-changing
千變萬化
If you say big sugar dry
你如果說大糖乾去
How many kinds does it have
它到底有幾種
Types of sugar outside
外面的糖的種類
Hundreds of
上百種
Hundreds of each
每一個都上百種
we just look at
我們只是看說
What kind of
到底是哪幾種
That is to say, initially there were 7
就是說最初是7架
these 7
這7個
These 7 kinds
這7種
Streptococcus pneumoniae
肺炎鏈球菌
nosocomial infection
比較會在院內感染
Play these 7 kinds first
先打這7種
In the future you will put these 7 kinds
未來你把這7種
After crushing it?
壓掉之後呢
anything else
別的就
other species will
別的種就會
in charge
執掌
So add 13 more
所以再加變成13種
plus 23 kinds
再加變成23種
so
所以
These vaccines are not absolute, you still follow
這些疫苗也不是絕對你還是跟
False progress is racing
虛進在賽跑
It's a good thing the research is endless, or I'd be out of a job.
還好研究是做不完的不然我就失業了
right
對不對
What this research can't do is to fight like this
這研究做不完的就是這樣子在對抗
by bwd6
by bwd6
good
好
Teacher Wu has two questions about Niu Zhang Chi
吳老師有兩個問題有關牛章癡的
The first question is that the octopus fungus grows on ordinary wood
第一個問題是說牛章菌它長在一般的木頭上面
What's the difference between growing on the ox octopus
跟長在牛章木上面到底有什麼不同
The second problem is its toxicity to Niu Zhang Chi
第二個問題是對於牛章癡它的毒性
Is it to the extent that it will hurt people?
到底有沒有會傷害到人的程度
Because I'm not a fanatic
因為我不是專門做牛章癡
so sorry it's hard for me to answer your question
所以很抱歉我很難回答你這個問題
When I have retired colleagues who do just that
當我有退休的同事專門做這一方面
he knows better than me
他就比我清楚得多
I may answer wrong here
我在這邊回答大概會回答錯
because i don't know much
因為我不太了解
I'm crazy about being a cow
我對於做牛章癡
People have done a lot
人家已經做了很多了
I just came in to do it
我才進來做
But what I do is limit in Duotang
但是我做的只有極限在多堂
There are many others like tri-iron
其他還有很多像什麼三鐵類啊
A bunch of them, what are you doing?
一堆啦 造乾啊什麼那一堆
Well, to be honest, I don't understand enough.
那個呢說實在的真的我不夠了解
Sorry I can't answer your question
非常抱歉沒辦法回答你的問題
ok ask again
好 再問
thanks ok i have a question is it ok to have a punch
謝謝好 我有一個問題有一個衝可以嗎
One question is about experts H1N1
一個問題是有關專家H1N1
So do these numbers have any special significance?
那請問這些數字有特別的意義嗎
What is the N level? Does the N level have any special meaning?
什麼N級 N級有沒有特別的意思
Thanks
謝謝
is there any special meaning
有沒有特別的意思
what does that mean
那意思就是什麼
I don't know about N1 and N2
我不清楚N1跟N2
because that is in fact
因為那事實上就是
The difference in the sequence of amino acid caused his this
安基酸次序的不不一樣造成他這個
Antibodies produced by blood type will be different
血液血型產生抗體會不一樣
sorry i don't know
抱歉我不知道耶
Now that means in 1918 it was N1 H1
現在就是說在1918年是N1 H1
There was also a pandemic in 1957
在1957年也有一次大流行
it is N2 H2
它是N2 H2
There was also a pandemic in 1968
1968年也有一次大流行
That one I remember is H2 H3 N2
那個我記得是H2 H3 N2
then what
還是什麼
Then in the end it is 1 2 3 in the end
那到底它這個1 2 3到底
I think it's a category
我想是一個分類吧
it's not different
它不是不一樣
Its Ankywan sequence is not the same cause
它的安基灣次序不一樣造成
because it's protein
因為它都是蛋白
So it is possible that H1 N1 will come back
所以有可能H1 N1也會回頭過來
possible
有可能
still never come back
還是絕對不會回頭過來
Probably will come back
應該也會回頭吧
I can not do it
我做不到
will look back
會回頭
That is H1 N1 is just in H1 N1
就是H1 N1就在H1 N1
likely to reappear
有可能在再出現
show up again
再出現是吧
another comment
另外一個comment
About Lushan
有關魯山的部分
I'm sorry, I'm Lu Shan
對不起 我有做魯山的
yes
是
perch acid
就是鱸糖的鱸酸
Exercising only when you are tired
就是疲勞的時候才能運動
Perch acid can only be produced under anaerobic metabolism
在無氧代謝的時候才能鱸酸
the research we did
那我們做的研究
we use
我們用
We do sports nutrition research
我們做運動營養研究
Then we do exhaustion exercise
那我們做衰竭的運動
Wale Train athletes
Wale Train的運動員
It's the mountain iron player
就是山鐵的選手
his fatigue
他的疲勞
to perch acid to achieve a bath of high quality
到鱸酸達到一個浴質很高
it's dying
它就要衰竭
Its very high concentration of perch acid
它這個很高的濃度的鱸酸
It clears up in about 15 to 20 minutes
大概在15到20分鐘就會清除掉
stop and clear
停下來就會清除掉
won't wait until the next day
不會等到第二天
So fast
這麼快
so it this
所以它這個
its perch
它的鱸酸就
so tired the next day
所以第二天疲勞
It's not because of perch
不是因為鱸酸的關係
It's because of the action of delayed onset muscle acid
是因為延遲性肌肉酸的動作
delayed muscle soreness
延遲肌肉酸所導致的
because of a muscle injury
是因為肌肉受傷的
So it has nothing to do with perch
所以跟鱸酸不是相干
so no reference
所以不用參考
Thanks
謝謝
here
這邊
Hello Professor Wu
吳教授您好
My problem is just that
我的問題是剛那個
The controgated vaccine of Numococcus
Numococcus的那個controgated vaccine
he
他
I'm curious about his carrier
我很好奇就是他的那個carrier
what will it be
會是什麼樣的東西
and hit us inside
然後打到我們身體裡面
because we also develop some antibodies to it
因為我們也會對它產生一些抗體
what kind of thing is it
它是一個什麼樣的東西
We feel it's a safe way to use this
我們覺得它是一個可以用很安全這樣
This is because of the carrier protein
這個 因為carrier protein它
fixed
有固定的
like rhinotoxin
就像白猴毒素
after it detoxifies
它把它去毒性之後
many people are using
很多人在用
becomes a carrier protein
就變成一個carrier protein
even you can buy
甚至你可以買得到
then why use this
那為什麼用這個
This detoxified white monkey is toxic
這個去毒的白猴毒性
I'm thinking that someone missed the research
我在想應該是人家有錯過研究
Well, I don't have a big problem with this aspect.
那我對這一方面倒沒有很大的
Research
研究
So it is the detoxification of the white monkey
所以它是白猴的去毒
That
那
One of these is a white monkey
這其中一種是白猴的
Then the carrier vaccine we used
那我們用的這個carrier vaccine
will it be
會不會就
Although the white monkey is almost out of muscle
雖然白猴已經快絕肌了
But do we also develop antibodies against it?
但是我們是不是也會給它產生抗體
a bit curious
有點令人好奇
of course
當然會
Because it's still a foreign antigen?
因為它還是外來的抗原嗎
I'm addressing the question asked by the lady just in front of me
我在針對剛剛前面那位女士問的問題
I remember that H
我印象中那個H
It is Hema Glutinin
就是Hema Glutinin
Is it related to Host specificity?
它是有跟Host specificity有關是不是
H123 seems to be the key to open the Human Flu
就是H123好像是打開那個Human Flu的鑰匙
And that H57 is the key to Avian Flu
然後那個H57是Avian Flu的鑰匙
We'll simply say
我們會這樣子簡單說
Yes, but many people at the scene should know
對 但是現場應該很多人知道
So I play big swords in front of sightseeing
所以我在觀光面前耍大刀
ok thank you sir
好 謝謝那位先生
yes
是
The one I want to ask is just about Cerule protein
那個我想要問一下就是剛剛講到Cerule protein
The teacher said that Cerule protein can last longer
老師說Cerule protein可以效果比較久
Because it can start the memory of the Tc package
是因為它可以啟動Tc包的記憶
Then everyone will explain in detail
那各位就是再詳細的解釋一下
Because I don't know much about the intermediate process
因為我不太清楚就這個中間的過程
I don't think I'm an immunologist
我覺得我不是一個免疫學家
to help you explain this
要幫你解釋這個
I'm afraid I can't explain it clearly.
恐怕沒辦法解釋得很清楚
but this is
但是這個是
If we put it into this
如果我們把它放到這個
at this place
在這個地方
If it is a multiple hall
它如果是一個多堂的話
It can't be B
它沒辦法就是B
It has no way to Present is
它沒辦法Present就是
MHC2 here
MHC2這邊
It has no way to generate this to follow B
它沒辦法產生這個來跟B
Come talk to T
來跟T對話
If you only have multiple halls
如果你是只有多堂的話
If you are Duotang
那你如果是多堂
If you are a carbohydrate antigen
如果你是糖質抗原
attached to protein
接在蛋白上面
Connected to this Protonite
接在這個Protonite
it can
它就有可以
After B can talk to T
B可以跟T對話完之後
T cells in
T細胞在
secrete some
分泌一些
in the looking what is this Chinese
in the looking這個中文是什麼
Boundary number
界白數
and then stimulate this
然後再來刺激這個
So the main difference is whether he can perform
所以說主要的差異是他能不能表現
It is the expression of this antigen that causes him to be
就是表現這個抗原造成他就是
difference in the effect of memory
記憶的效果的差異
i know now
我現在知道是這樣
But I just said I'm not an immunologist
但是我剛剛講過我不是免疫學家
Maybe there are immunologists here
搞不好有在座的免疫學家
can help me answer
可以幫我回答
Then I'll go find it myself
那我自己再去找
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
High school textbooks say that the B cell
高中課本是說那個B cell
If it is a polysaccharide antigen
如果是多醣性的抗原的話
B cell is to do the receptor mediated endocytosis
B cell它是做那個receptor mediated endocytosis
Then activate to become that plasma cell
然後自己activate變成那個plasma cell
But then it can't use that mc
但這樣它就不能用那個mc
to present antigen
去呈現抗原
去activate specific dehelper
去activate specific dehelper
so it doesn't have that
所以它就沒有那個
it still produces specific antibodies
它還是會產生特定的抗體
there is no merry
就沒有merry
But the main thing is to understand why
不過主要是想要了解是為什麼就是
If you add QQ protein to QQ protein
QQ protein 就加QQ protein的話
It can be started but if it is not added
可以啟動可是如果不加的話
It is more difficult to express
它就比較難法就是表現
thank you thank you teacher
謝謝 謝謝老師
here for sir
這裡是為了先生
Mr. Wu would like to ask you for advice
吳老師想跟你請教一下
Just now you talked about that EPO
剛剛你談到那個EPO
Can we talk a little more about the kidneys?
跟腎臟可不可以再多談一點
For example, the one
譬如說有的那個
Kidney dialysis patients will have flat blood
洗腎的人會有平血的狀況
About the relationship between EPO and the kidney
有關EPO跟腎臟之間的關係
Teacher, can you talk a little more?
老師可不可以多講一點
like erythrocyte renin
像紅血球腎臟素
because
因為
Kidney dialysis man
洗腎的人他
This one from EPO
EPO的這個
Erythrocyte renin will be less
紅血球腎臟素就會比較少
because he is the most important
因為他最主要
Epo is secreted from our kidney cells
Epo是從我們的腎臟細胞分泌
Then the kidney cells of your kidney dialysis person will be
那你洗腎的人你的腎臟細胞就
will be weaker
就會比較弱了嘛
he can't have
他就沒辦法有
Appropriate amount out
適當的量出來
then if you have
那這時候你如果有
If the doctor gives you an injection
醫婆給你注射的話
Your red blood cell count will increase
你紅血球的量就會增高
Then your normal blood will be relieved
那這時候你平血就會減輕
you will be more energetic
你會比較有活力
Because after all, red blood cells are
因為畢竟紅血球是
Oxygen?
代氧的嘛
We know oxygen consumption
我們知道氧氣的消耗
It has a lot to do with our energy
跟我們的能量是非常有關係的
ask a question
請教一個問題
That is to say, it is mentioned that it is cow's dirty juice
就是說有提到就是牛髒汁
And that black fungus
還有那個黑木耳
Its polysaccharides are activated
它的多糖都有活化
The function of that megalithic cell
那個巨石細胞的功能
then i want to ask
那我想要請教一下說
I don't know if it has been compared
我不知道有沒有比較過
The two sources of polysaccharides
這個兩個來源的多糖
Does it work differently
它的效果有沒有不一樣
and because we know
然後因為我們知道
Does beef offal seem expensive?
牛髒好像很貴嘛
Then I asked if I should actually eat more black fungus
然後說是不是其實多吃一點黑木耳
it's ok
就可以了
Thanks
謝謝
can you help me answer this question
你有沒有可不可以幫我回答這個問題
In fact, other effective
事實上牛章之他有效的
People have always believed that the effective ingredients are not only multitasking
人家一直覺得有效的成份不是只有多他
But because I want to be different from other people who study
但是我因為要跟其他研究的人有所區隔
Because people are making too many other active ingredients
因為人家在做其他的有效成份已經做太多了
The person who studied Niu Zhangzhi has been in Taiwan for a long time
牛章之研究的人在台灣已經很久了
But I haven't seen anyone who does multiple halls come out.
但是我是一直沒看到有做多堂的人出來
The reason is that it is definitely not that simple for you to understand the structure of Duotang
理由是因為多堂你要解他的結構絕對不是那麼簡單
That's why we thought we'd try and see what we put in to do this
所以我們才覺得我們試試看我們投入做這樣
I want to differentiate myself from other researchers
想要說跟其他的研究者有所區隔
If you separate, you are more effective
區隔的話就是你比較有效的
Opportunity to receive research funding from the Ministry of Science and Technology
有機會拿到科技部的研究經費
different from everyone
跟大家做的不一樣
I use this idea to do this research
我是用這個想法去做這個研究
In fact, the research time is quite long.
事實上研究的時間也蠻長的
It will probably take three or four years
大概也要耗掉三四年
A doctoral student wants to
一個博士班學生要
Those two things take four years in a doctoral program
那兩個東西在一個博士班要做到四年
to finish it
才可以把它做完
there is a gentleman behind
後面有一位先生
sorry, i want to ask
不好意思,我想請問一下
can explain a little bit
可以稍微說明一下
When we study sugar
我們在研究糖類的時候
The process of storage and separation
存化跟分離的過程
Because sugars are not like amino acids in proteins
因為糖不像蛋白質的胺基酸一樣
there is only one solution
就是只有一種解法
it can have many solutions
它可以有很多種解法
And there are not only twenty types of sugar
而且糖也不只二十種
So you can ask me a little bit
所以可以稍微請教一下
how to actually do
要實際上要怎麼做
How to do
要怎麼做
It is the method of storing and identifying
是存化跟辨識的方法
is to recognize the difference
就是辨識這個分別
generally like sugar
一般來講像糖
Sugar research is slow to find
糖研究是慢找的
but progress is slow
但是進展得很慢
But recently progress is faster
但是最近進展比較快
Progress is slow for two reasons
進展很慢的理由有兩個
Because your chemistry didn't keep up
因為你化學沒有跟上
like this
像這個
For protein
對蛋白來講
Its synthesis can be automated
它的合成可以自動化
After the 80s
那到了80年代之後
genetic function
又可以用遺傳功能的方式
to produce the protein of our medicine
去產生我們藥的蛋白
that for this DNA
那對於這個DNA
or RNA speaking
或者RNA來講的話
Also because of the synthetic technique
也是因為合成的技術
and we say
還有我們說
How do you say PCR is a table in Chinese?
PCR是桌中文怎麼講
right
對
ex girl
前女生
After these developments
這些進展之後
So DNA
所以DNA
The research on this nucleic acid should be done as much as possible
這個核酸的研究就大要盡
So sugar is the first one you can detect, you can’t detect it
所以糖來講 第一個你偵測 測不到
because we're detecting proteins and nucleic acids
因為我們在偵測蛋白跟核酸
We can use ultraviolet light
我們用紫外光就可以
But with sugar you can't detect it in ultraviolet light
但對於糖來講你偵測不到 在紫外光
Therefore, it is an obstacle to both analysis and synthesis.
所以對於分析 合成都是障礙
That is the way you said just now.
也就是剛剛你說的 它的接法
You probably only have at most two ways of connecting two amino acids.
你兩個氨酸接法大概只有頂多兩種
One N segment and one C segment at most two
一個N段一個C段頂多兩種
Go see if one amino acid becomes two amino acids
你去看 如果一個氨酸變成兩個氨酸
In terms of diamine, it is a kind of
雙氨來講的話就是一種
But sugar, a monosaccharide linked to a disaccharide
但是糖 一個單糖接成雙糖
it has eleven types so its complexity is high
它有十一種 所以它的複雜性很高
And it's a lot more indirect like Avaboda Iii Izo
而且它間接很多 像阿伐伯達 伊二 伊三
It's complicated, but it's really inside a living organism
很複雜 但是真正在生物體裡面
not that complicated
沒有那麼複雜
why
為什麼呢
Because he wants to pick up a Tang sword
因為他要接一個唐劍
He's wasting a gene
他要耗掉一個基因
pick him up to make one
接他要合成一個
synthesized like you
像你合成
At once
就
Alpha medical affairs
阿法醫事
or Beta Medicine
或者Beta醫事
is to consume a gene
就是要耗掉一個基因
is a valid number
就是一個效數
to lead this
要來主導這個
people
人
Genes are coded
基因都結碼了
forming Tang sword
形成唐劍的
about 200
大概200
various efficacies
多種不同的效數
we call this
我們把這個叫做
Glycoxial Transverse
Glycoxial Transverse
how to translate
應該怎麼翻譯
That's about 200 or so
那大概只有200多個
so
所以
you can watch
你可以看
his true presence
他的真正在
The structure is not so complicated
的結構沒有那麼複雜
I think
我覺得
The hard part is
難的地方是在於
Modifications on the Tang Sword
唐劍上面的修飾
this is difficult
這個是難
A single hyaluronic acid
單單一個透益酸
he was groomed probably
他被修飾大概
there is
就有
Forty or fifty ways of repairing
四五十種的修制方式
this is hard
這個才是很難
If you just modify it
你只要一修飾的話
Its combination with the number of coagulation poles changes the
它跟凝極數的結合就改變了
any modification
隨便一個修飾
So the difficulty is here
所以難度高是在這裡
I think it's very difficult because
我覺得這個難度很高是在
As for the real Tang Jian?
至於說這個真正的唐建怎麼
sometimes if you have
有時候你如果有的話
You can also send it to help others.
送去幫人家做也可以
1,500 yuan broke two days without gold
一千五百塊破兩天沒金
They did it for you
人家就幫你做了
Do you have any other questions
還有什麼問題嗎
Just now it seems that there is someone thinking about Fangwen in the back
剛剛好像後面有想方文的
Wait a moment
等一下
I just talked about the Dotang vaccine
剛剛有講到多唐疫苗
For the elderly and children under the age of two
對於老年人跟兩歲以下小孩子
Effect
效果
Why is his effect on these two ethnic groups less effective?
他為什麼針對這兩個族群效果比較不好
Then there is his so-called short effect
那還有他的所謂的效果短
If the effect is short, how short is it?
效果短的話是短到什麼程度
Then for such an application on the pre-hospital study
那對醫房預學上面的這樣一個運用
What kind of applicable timing?
到底什麼樣的適用時機呢
that is
就是
this is really sorry
這個真的很抱歉
because I
因為我
first i am not a doctor
第一個我不是醫生
The dean of liufu is actually a doctor
留復院長事實上是醫生
It seems to say that only polysaccharides are used instead of that
好像是說是只用多糖體而不用那個
You can do it without Count
不用Count就可以
no carrier
不用Carrier
is it not good
就不好嗎
still the same as before
還是跟剛才的一樣
The carrier is to increase his immunity
就是Carrier是增加他的免疫力
Will cause T-cell Response
會造成T-cell的Response
Then T-cell is T helper
然後T-cell是T helper的話
It is Hel B-cell
是Hel B-cell
This kind of concept about this kind
這種關於這種Concept
Simply put it like this
簡單的就講起來就這樣子
Then at this stage
那這階段的話
Because just now we talked about 23 and 13
因為剛剛有談到23架跟13架
Since these two are polysaccharide vaccines and conjugate vaccines, there is a difference
既然這兩種就是多糖疫苗跟結合疫苗有差別
Then there are products on his food now?
那他食物上現在有產品出來是
for is
針對是
Is it really a polysaccharide vaccine?
真正是多糖疫苗的嗎
is there such a
有沒有這樣一個
you say
你說
It should be NUEMO COCKER
應該是NUEMO COCKER的
Vaccine is polysaccharide
Vaccine的話他是多糖的
13 is
13架是
come to get a vaccine
come to get a vaccine
is a conjugate vaccine
是結合疫苗
Yeah, he just talked about a 23 frame being polysaccharide
對 他剛剛有談到一個23架是多糖的
right
對
23 is the same
23架也是一樣
is also a carrier
也是carrier
Is it also a carrier?
也是carrier嗎
yes yes no
對 是不是 是不是
No information I see is
沒有 我看到的資料是
yes he is more than one
是他是一個多
a polisacra
一個polisacra
what's his name
他的名字叫做什麼
You have a vaccine Samyam
You have a vaccine Samyam
Yeah
對對對
I
我
no no no this
不是 不是不是這
he is this
他是這個
PPV?
PPV嘛
He's PPV so a polisacra vaccine
他是PPV 所以是一個polisacra vaccine
Is this information wrong? I don't know
這個資料有錯嗎 我不知道
The mayor mayor can already have 23
市長市長可以已經有23架了
There are 23
有23架
The range of protection is about 80%
那保護的範圍大概8成多
8 Narita
8成多
Because it's short-acting but I don't know how short-acting it is
因為它短效 但是我不曉得 它是短效到什麼程度
this may be
這個可能要再
Short-acting sometimes varies from person to person
短效 有時候會因人而異啦
I don't know, I really don't know
我也不知道啦 我真的不太清楚
good committee
好 沈委
our last question
我們最後一個問題
I remember we commemorate the pneumonia vaccine
我記得我們紀念打肺炎那個疫苗
It means that you only need to play once in a lifetime, it seems
它是說一輩子只要打一次 好像
Then if it was these 23 fights, it was short-term
那如果是打的是這23架 又是短效
Why only fight once in a lifetime
為什麼一輩子只要打一次
that's a really good question
這真的是一個好問題
Pneumonia doesn't seem to be just one shot all the time
肺炎好像不是一直打一次而已
Because I played it myself, I still need boost
因為我自己打過 所以還是要boost
Another problem is that hospital infection
另外一個問題就是那個醫院感染
Because when my father was 89 years old
因為我父親他89歲的時候
never get sick just because it is
從來不生病 就因為是
Constipation entered the hospital for seven days and left
便秘進了醫院七天就走了
The final result is nosocomial infection
最後的結果就是說院內感染
Then we ask that your ward be cleaned again for me.
那我們要求說你病房給我再清洗一遍
or what can we do
還是怎麼樣我們能做什麼
It was our doctor who brought the bacteria
還是我們看病的人帶了細菌去的
No, I think the bacteria was already in the hospital.
不是 我是覺得那個菌本來就在醫院裡面
Because of that bacteria, look, you're in the hospital
因為那個菌 你看嘛你在醫院
You sterilize, and then everyone brings the bacteria in
你消毒啊 然後大家都把菌帶進去
And then the bacterium is its genetic material that gets passed around
然後細菌是它的遺傳物質會傳來傳去的
Then you and your disinfection is to make it have the power of evolution
那你又 你消毒就是讓它有進化的力量嘛
Right, so it evolves more and more powerful
對不對 所以它越進化越厲害
It if you kill 99% of the bacteria
它如果 細菌你殺掉99%
You still survive in large numbers, it's even stronger
你還是大量的存活下來的 它更厲害
I don't know if the health insurance has statistics
不知道健保有沒有統計
How many elderly people died of hospital infection
究竟多少老年人在院內感染而去世的
We would also like to have such public information to allow
我們也希望有這樣的公開資訊讓
We patients know that I am old
我們病人知道說我年紀大了
Should I go to the hospital or not?
我到底要不要進醫院
or how
或者怎麼樣
What's the reason to go to the hospital
什麼情況才要進醫院
Can you make your delivery a little longer?
是不是可以讓自己運貨長一點
this is one
這個倒是一個
you're sick of course you want to go to the hospital
你生病當然你想要去醫院嗎
What about going to the hospital?
那去醫院呢
Afraid of nosocomial infection
又怕被院內感染
what do you do
那你怎麼辦呢
this is a good question
這個是一個好問題
I don't know what the doctor will decide
不知道醫生會怎麼決定
Or to become a style news
或是要變成一個風格的訊
I sometimes think so
我有時候會這樣想
i've been thinking about this
我一直在想這個問題
because sometimes you have to decide
因為有的時候你要決定
what medicine do you take
你要用什麼藥
Because you want to see what bacteria
因為你要看是什麼菌
what medicine
用什麼藥
doctor he has
醫生他有
so i always feel like saying
所以我一直覺得說
in this hospital
在這個醫院裡面
nosocomial infection bacteria
有院內感染的菌
should be announced
應該都公佈出來
Then sometimes if you have to decide what bacteria
那有時候你如果要決定是什麼菌的話
it may be days before you find out
你可能要好幾天之後才知道
This patient may have left
這個病人都已經可能就走了
So I've always wondered if there's a way to do a quick quick screening
所以我一直覺得有沒有辦法做很快的快篩
can determine what bacteria it is
能夠決定它是什麼菌
Then we quickly dose
然後我們再迅速的用藥
it's possible to bring it back
就有可能把它救回來
this is what i don't know
這個就是我不知道
I have been wondering if there is a better way
我一直在想看有沒有比較好的方法
I would like to add a little bit to the issue of nosocomial infection
我想稍微補充一下院內感染這個問題
Nosocomial infection actually involves two parts
院內感染其實牽涉到兩個部分
One is the use of antibiotics
一個是抗育素的使用
the resistance it produces
它所產生的抗藥性
The other one, of course, is the patient's resistance
另外一個當然也是病人的抵抗力
So the question asked by this partner just now
所以剛剛這位夥伴所問的問題
If you want to announce this part
如果要公告這個部分
It is actually on the one hand
它其實一方面
In fact, there is not that high evidence that
其實也沒有那麼高的證據就是說
Which bacteria is actually causing
哪一個細菌是真正造成
Because of the drug that caused the infection and even caused death
因為那個感染甚至造成死亡的用藥
reason because if he really would cause death
原因 因為如果他真的會造成死亡
He may be the so-called cluster infection
他可能就是所謂的群聚感染
instead of just one or two patients dying from this bacterium
而不會只有一兩個病人因為這個細菌而過世
So it involves his personal immunity
所以牽涉他個人的免疫力
So this is what he wants to pursue
所以這一種就是他要追究到
Going back to medical reasons, he may have many layers
回到醫學的原因的話他可能有很多層次
Reducing nosocomial infections is like what the teacher, Mr. Wu, just said
減少醫院感染就像剛剛老師 吳老師所講的
In fact, hand washing is a very important key step
其實洗手是一個很重要的關鍵步驟
How to cut off or wear a mask in the hospital
怎麼樣去切斷或是在醫院裡面戴口罩
Avoid direct infections on the nose and mouth
避免直接口鼻上的感染
These are the basics, that is to say, you can do it yourself in the hospital.
這些都是基礎的 就是說在醫院裡面自己會做
Then we patients have to protect ourselves when we go in.
那我們病人進去自己也要保護自己
Probably such a situation
大概是這樣子的一個狀況
Thanks
謝謝
Today is live
今天是有現場直播
So there are already viewers asking questions
所以已經有觀眾問問題
ask questions to everyone
對 大家問問題
you see a lot of fans
你看很多粉絲
One question is how the longan is added to the protein
一個問題是長內要如何被加在蛋白質上
is your profession
就是你的專業
How to add sugar to protein
有糖糖怎麼樣加在蛋白質上
very simple
很簡單
he added to the protein
他加在蛋白的上
He has specific mainly two places
他有特定主要是兩個地方
Two kinds of security
兩種安基收
how to add sugar how to add
怎麼樣加到糖怎麼樣加到
that candy
那個糖
don't recognize you help me answer
不認到你幫我回答
no no no no added to protein what is
沒有沒有沒有加到蛋白是什麼
I didn't know this guy is sometimes your specialty
我不知道這個人有時候是你的專業
This is added in this Guoju Paris
這個就是在這個郭居巴黎加的
this his problem is
這個他的問題是
Yes, I don’t know how it is added in the cells
對對不曉得是在細胞裡面怎麼加上去的
how to add in the cell
是在細胞裡面怎麼加
I don't know what the problem is
我不知道這個問題是
What is added in the high-vision body
那高視體裡面加的
yes the question is
對問題是
How to add it in the cell
如果在細胞裡面怎麼加上去的話
That's what you just mentioned
那就是剛你提的這個這個
Hook and squeeze
勾擠勾擠
Guo Ju Paris
郭居巴黎
pick up
接的
on the ER
在ER上面
What about answering?
接的話呢
rely on eyebrows
要靠眉
by eyebrow
靠眉嘛
Yep
對對
By eyebrow
靠眉
if it's chemistry
如果是化學的話
chemical words
化學的話
chemical basis
化學基礎
yes yes go to the basics
對對對去基礎的
right
對
Yeah
對對對
yes but
對但是
It's not that simple if you're using chemistry
如果你是用化學的話也沒有那麼簡單
like we just said
像我們剛剛說的
If you want to fight, give it
要把要做抗就給
It's the conjugate vaccine
就是結合疫苗的話
just add
就就是這樣加
just to
就是要把
we are added
我們是加在
the one above lysine
離安酸上面的那個
Like you said
就像你說的
Lighting above
Lighting上面的
Eminogur
Eminogur
Of course there must be something to activate it
當然要有一些把它活化嘛
right
對
Or you can be a Linker
或是可以做個Linker
then the sugar is
然後糖是
Generally speaking, we need Linker
一般來講我們要有Linker
This Linker chooses
這個Linker選擇又
Very Picky
很Picky
This Linker option cannot
這個Linker選擇又不能
Linker it
Linker它的
Antigenetic too high
Antigenetic太高
also not
也不行
That is to say, it is easy to produce Antibodyzo
就是說它很容易產生Antibodyzo也不行
many such options
很多這種選擇
a lot to think about
要考慮就很多了
well, we're running out of time
好我們時間也差不多了
thank you
謝謝各位
Then we once again thank Wu Zhixiong for his very mentality speech
那我們再次謝謝吳志雄模式的非常心態演講
Thanks
謝謝
The preview I need to make is knowledge miss in June
我需要做的預告就是6月份的知識想念
The topic of the talk is Hu Shi and Li Ao
講題是拍在我去的胡適與李敖
Interactions Between Two Generations of Liberals in Taiwan
台灣兩代自由主義者之間的交往
Is the keynote speaker of the Huang Kewu Special Research Fellow at the Institute of Modern History
是在近代史研究所黃克武特別研究員的主講人
Please sign up to attend this speech
也請大家踴躍報名參加來聽這個演講
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Thanks
謝謝